Academia Sinica's 2023 Governor's Vision
中央研究院2023年知事想驗
Dean Wang Shijie's popular science lecture begins
王世傑院長科普講座開始
We have asked Vice President Huang Jingxin to host for us
我們有請黃靜新副院長為我們主持
The 132nd birthday of President Wang Shijie Gu
這個王世傑顧院長132歲名誕
In order to express our memory and respect for President Wang
為表達我們對王院長的追思和敬意
At this time of year
本院每年此時
commemorative lectures will be held
都會舉辦紀念演講
President Wang Shijie is the fourth president of the hospital
王世傑院長是本院第四任院長
During his term of office, he made every effort to promote academic cooperation between China and the United States
他在任內全力推動中美學術合作
Yannan Overseas Outstanding Scholars Return to Taiwan to Give Lectures
延南海外優秀學者回台講學
Qiu Jianzhong's Center for American Studies
仇建中的包括有美國研究中心
Institute of Europe and America
現在為歐美研究所
It is also the service unit of Wang Fu Research Institute
也是王副研究院服務的單位
This establishment has been established for more than 50 years
這個所設立已經超過50年
It also hosts the Economic Research Institute
它也籌設了經濟研究所
Institute of Restoration Physics, etc.
恢復物理研究所等
For the cultivation of national talents and the improvement of science and technology, the influence is self-fulfilling
為國家人才培育及科學技術的提升影響自圓
tonight's keynote speaker
今晚的主講人士
Associate Researcher Wang Zhiming of the Institute of European and American Studies
本院歐美研究所的王志明副研究員
He graduated from the Department of Foreign Languages, National Tsing Hua University
他畢業於國立清華大學外文系
M.A. in Comparative Literature from National Taiwan University
以國立台灣大學取得比較文學碩士
Care about University of California, Santa Claus
在乎美國加州大學Santa Claus
Ph.D.
分校取得文學博士學位
Now it is the European and American Institute of our hospital
現在為本院歐美研究所
Institute of Social Culture, Yangming Jiaotong University
以陽明交通大學社會文化研究所
He hired each other as professors
和聘互教授
He is elected from 2021 to 2022
他在2021年到2022年獲選
Visiting scholar of China Experience Society
中國驗經學社訪問學者
it's an honor
這是一個榮譽
Once in 2017 to 2018
曾經在2017到2018
single segment
單段
Visiting scholar of China Academy of Art
中國美術學院的訪問學人
Researcher Wang Fu mainly studies Lin Wei
王富研究員主要研究林以為
Asian American Literature
亞裔美國文學
Colonial Theory after Agenda Cultural Studies
亞紀文化研究以後殖民理論
recent interest
近年的興趣
Turning to Jiangjie Geopolitics
轉向江界地緣政治
as a refugee
以難民意提等
His writings are very rich
他的著作十分的豐富
its tyranny
其專制
Landed in foreign language studies in Taiwan
落地轉易臺灣外文研究的
Centennial trajectory
百年軌跡
Take the Foreign Languages ​​Department of National Taiwan University as an example
以臺大外文系為例
Exploring the Cold War
探究冷戰時期
Native European and American Literature
本土歐美文學
Curriculum Planning and the Political Operations in It
課程規劃以其中的政治操作
In last year 2022
在去年2022年
Humanities and Social Sciences
獲得本院人文及社會科學
academic book chief
學術性專書長
it's very competitive
這是競爭很激烈
also national
也是全國性的
No wonder I look familiar to you
難怪我對你看起來很面熟
Because I'm giving this award
因為我就頒這個獎
last year
在去年
He suddenly won the Academy's Humanities and Social Sciences Exclusive Award
他突而得了本院的人文社會可以專屬獎
This year
今年
There are universal gains in March
3月有普獲
National Science and Health Outstanding Research Award
國科衛傑出研究獎
also became 2014
也成為2014年
Won the Academy Young Writer Award
獲得本院年輕著作獎
2009 National Science Guard Wu Dayou Memorial Award
2009年國科衛吳大尤紀念獎
You have won all the awards in Taiwan
全台灣的獎你都拿遍了
and the 2008 American Studies Association
以及2008年美國研究學會
Shenyan Chubby International Scholars Paper Award
神言胖乎國際學者論文獎
what is his english
他的英文是什麼
What country is he Japanese from?
他是哪一國的日本人嗎
He is an outstanding and very young humanist scholar
是很優秀而且很年輕的人文學者
I won't say more
接下來我就不多說
Please give us a round of applause to welcome Wang Huyan to the rescue
請我們一掌聲歡迎王沪炎救援
Tell the story of this refugee
來講這個難民的故事
Power Freedom and Dignity Keynote Speeches
權力 自由與尊嚴 專題演講
Presumably exciting
想必精采可期
Then we sit together and listen
那我們就再坐在一起聆聽
thank you all
謝謝大家
Family members of Vice President Hua and then former President Wang Shijie
華副院長然後王世傑的前院長的家屬
And hello to all the audience friends here
以及在座的聽眾朋友大家好
Thank you so much friends for coming tonight
非常感謝今天各位朋友在今天晚上來到
I'm sorry, it's reversed
對不起 拿反了
Come to this occasion to hear this speech
來到這個場合來聽這個演講
That
那
Chen Rugang, Vice President Wang, talked about this period of time
陳如剛王副院長講的這一段時間
I saw him quite a lot
見到他的次數蠻多的
So I can recognize it if I want to
所以我願意就可以認得出來
special thanks to him
也特別謝謝他
because during this time
因為在這一段時間
including from to
包括從去
At the beginning of this visit, there are actually a lot of troubles to Vice President Huang's place.
這個訪問開始其實有很多地方麻煩到黃副院長的地方
Then let Vice President Huang be the host and introduce today
那今天能夠讓黃副院長擔任這個主持跟介紹
For me, it is actually a very, very great honor
對我來講其實是一個非常非常大的一個榮耀
Especially on such an occasion today is the commemorative lecture given by former President Wang Shijie
那特別是在今天這樣一個場合是王世傑前院長的這個紀念講座
As Vice President Wang mentioned just now, it means that Europe and the United States are actually in the
那如剛剛王副院長提到的就是說歐美索其實下是在
President Wang promoted the establishment of
王院長任內推動成立
And he is very concerned. In fact, this morning he even read some of the techniques in his diary.
而且他十分的關心其實今天早上還翻閱了他這個日記裡頭的一些技術
It can be seen that during the period from 1968 to 1969, he was constantly promoting and facilitating the establishment of such a new unit
可以看得到他在1968年1969年這段時間就不斷的在推動跟促成這樣一個新的單位的一個成立
So for me to be the host of this lecture today
所以今天能夠擔任這場講座的主長人對我來講
It's a great honor and a lot of pressure
是莫大的榮耀也是很大的壓力
never thought to say
從來沒有想到說
In fact, I have given so many speeches today, I feel that the special pressure is a little bit greater.
其實講了那麼多場的演講今天這場我覺得特別的壓力巨大一些
But today's speech has a big purpose, in fact, the research institute faces the public
但是今天這樣演講有一個很大的目的其實是研究院面對社會大眾
To make some such an attempt on the popularization of humanities
要進行一些關於人文科普方面這樣的一個嘗試
Then this also means that apart from doing its own research in the depths of Xiangyata, the research institute
那這也代表了研究院除了在這個向亞塔深處做自己的研究之外
In fact, we also hope that our research can bring some inspiration to the public and point to some different concerns.
其實我們也很希望我們的研究能夠帶給社會大眾一些啟發跟指向一些不同的關懷
Mr. Lin, who was here just now, reminded me that many friends may also be very concerned about this issue of refugees.
那剛在座的林老師還特別提醒我這個有很多朋友可能也很關心這個難民的議題
I am curious if the refugee issue I am talking about today is related to the practice of saving refugees in the real world
很好奇今天我講這個難民議題會不會跟現實世界當中拯救難民的這個實踐相關
Of course there are some details that are close, but there are also some big differences.
那這裡頭當然會有一些細節是接近的但是也會有一些滿大的差異
Then what I want to say is actually in the context of humanities science popularization
那我想要說的其實是整個在人文科普的這個脈絡當中
What I want to bring to you today is not so much about the experience of the refugees themselves
我今天想要帶給大家的與其說是關於難民本身的經驗
more is to want through literature
更多的是想要透過文學的
Learned such a perspective and media
學的這樣的一個視角跟媒材
how to discuss the story itself
去討論故事本身怎麼樣去
Shaping Refugees
形塑難民
And what about the refugees themselves
以及難民本身怎麼樣來講述
stories about themselves
關於他們自己的故事
then why talk about refugees
那為什麼要談難民
Why talk about refugees at this time
為什麼在今天這個時候談難民
Why put refugee stories in
為什麼要把難民故事放到
In today's historical time and space in Taiwan
在今天台灣的這個歷史時空的
Let's talk about this now
這個當下來談
I think
我覺得
I believe many, many friends
我相信很多很多的朋友
should feel
應該都會有所感觸
for me
對我來講
Discussion and development of this topic
這個題目的討論跟展開
actually in
其實是在
during my own research
就是我自己的研究過程當中
by reading in Yayi
透過閱讀在亞一
these writers who grew up in america
在美國成長的亞一的這些作家
They write their own
他們書寫他們自己的這種
so-called discrete experience
所謂的離散的經驗
especially vietnamese writers
特別是越南的作家
Talk about how they escaped from Vietnam
談他們怎麼樣從越南逃亡
came to america such a story
來到美國這樣的一個故事
And at the beginning I felt something about him
而一開始對他感覺到有一些的
interest and concern
興趣跟關懷
then it's a bigger trigger
那麼可是更大的一個觸發
Actually two years ago
其實是在兩年前
In other words, it was two years ago and three years ago in 2020
话说都是2020年两年前三年前的事情
That is, the United States will withdraw its troops from Afghanistan in August 2020
就是美国在2020年的8月从阿富汗撤军
I don't know if you guys still remember the scene of the withdrawal
我不知道各位还记不记得那个撤军的画面
The helicopter took off from that platform
直升机就在那个月台上起飞
Then there are the many Afghan people everywhere
然后有为处众多的阿富汗民众
or can't get into the airport
要么进不了机场
or can only wave on the platform
要么只能够在月台上面挥手
Or hope to catch the last class to leave Afghanistan
或者说希望能够搭上这个最后一班离开阿富汗的班级
So today in 2023
那么今天在2023年的今天
Taiwan is also facing the threat of war in a certain sense
台湾也在某一个意义上面面临了战争的威胁
Even when I accompanied Boxi to Taiwan last year
甚至在去年这个陪伯夕访台的时候
I even have a very apt feeling that
我甚至有一种很贴切的感觉是
in case something happens
万一发生了什么事
Will we become refugees too?
会不会我们也要变成难民
In this sense
那从这个意义上面
Just from such an experience
就从这样的一个经验上的一种体会
Makes me think about the refugee problem
让我觉得难民的问题
May not be those others who are waiting to be rescued in the distance
可能不是远在天边那些等待被救援的他者
It's right next to us and maybe even ourselves
而是就在我们身边甚至可能是我们自己
own history and process
自身的歷史跟過程
But let's hope it doesn't become our future
但我們希望它不會成為我們的未來
That's why I feel that from this time on
那也因此我覺得從這個時候開始
Concerns over refugee issues
對難民議題多所的關切
Perhaps it is at this time that Taiwan society
或許是在這個時候對台灣社會
a reminder that might be important
可能很重要的一個提醒
So let's talk a little bit more about this topic
那麼進一步稍微談一下這個題目
refugee story
難民故事
Of course the main character is a refugee
當然主角是難民
But at this angle of my entry
但是就我的切入的這個角度
more important may be the story itself
更重要的可能是故事本身
Then I'll put this part of the story back later
那待會我會再把這個故事的部分
Let me explain to you
跟大家做一個說明
Then in the subtitle
那麼副標題裡頭
power liberty and dignity
權力 自由跟尊嚴
In fact, several issues surrounding refugees
其實是幾個圍繞著難民議題
related concepts
相關的這些概念
For example, why do you want to become a refugee?
比方講為什麼要成為難民
why be a refugee
為什麼會成為難民
because of lack of freedom
是因為缺乏了自由
or hope for freedom
或是希望爭取自由
Why refugees deserve our attention
為什麼難民值得我們關注
because they are also subjects of power
是因為他們也是具有權力的主體
or worthy of our considerable power
或值得我們賦予他相當的這個權力
even the existence of refugees
甚至說難民的存在
He needs more than freedom and power
他所需要的不僅僅是自由跟權力
more
更多的
may be dignity
可能是尊嚴
those different levels
那這些不同的層面
Maybe it can help us to build a
或許可以幫助我們去構築一個
our one for refugees
我們對於難民的一個
A more three-dimensional understanding
比較立體的一個理解
So let me start today's talk
那麼就讓我開始展開今天的這個演講
I start with the W.H.O.D.N.
我先用W.H.O.D.N.
This is a poet in England at the beginning of the patriotic century
這個是英國在愛國世紀初期的一個詩人
is also a very famous modernist poet
也是一個非常著名的這個現代派詩人
Have traveled to China
曾經到過中國旅行
And then there are some interesting ones like these
然後還有一些很有趣的這些
what is this called
這個叫什麼
poet's love relationship
詩人的愛戀關係
But love relationships I'm not here today
但是愛戀關係我今天就不在這邊展開來
Simply put, in the 1930s
簡單講在30年代
He actually paid attention to this
他其實就關注到了這個
The so-called German
所謂的當時從德國
these jewish refugees from central europe
從歐洲中部離開的這些猶太難民
Then I wrote such a poem
那麼也是寫下了這麼一首詩
I simply translate a little bit
我簡單的稍微翻譯一下
He said there are tens of millions of souls in this city
他說這個城市有上千萬的這個靈魂
but also live in these
但是同樣住在這些
But some people live in mansion villas
但有一些人住在大廈別墅裡頭
some people live in mansions
有些人住在大廈
live in a hole
住在洞裡頭
Then what
然後呢
for us
對我們來講呢
In fact, we are the group of people who have no place to live.
其實我們是沒有地方住的那群人
And we're the ones who don't have a place to live
然後我們是沒有地方住的那群人
that once we had a country
那曾經我們有過一個國家
And we also used to think it was beautiful
然後我們也曾經覺得它很美麗
But look at this map right now
但是看看現在眼前的這個地圖
you can also find where it is
你還能夠找到它在哪裡
but we can't go there
可是我們不能夠去那裡
honey we can't go there
親愛的 我們不能夠去那裡
On the grave in this village
在這個村莊裡頭的墳墓上
An old red mountain tree like this grows
長了一棵老的這種紅山樹
every spring
每一個每一年春天
it will re-germinate and re-grow
它都會重新的發芽 重新的生長
But what about our old passports?
但是呢 我們身上的舊的護照呢
won't regrow
不會重新的生長
Our old passports don't grow back
我們舊的護照不會重新的生長
These officials of this half times
這個半次數的這些官員
knock and talk tell us
敲著說著跟我們說
if you don't have a passport
如果你沒有護照的話
Then you are speaking from an official point of view
那你就是從官方的角度來說
you no longer exist
你就不存在了
but we're still here baby
但是我們還在這裡啊 親愛的
but we're still here
但是我們還在這裡啊
Then this is his care and concern for the Jewish refugees at that time
那這個是他對當時對猶太難民的一個關懷跟關注
Then let us also see
那麼也讓我們看到
refugee to refugee
難民對難民的這個
In terms of description, there are actually a lot of layers
描述來說其實有很大的層次
A big part of it is actually his lack of power.
很大的部分其實是在於他缺乏了權利
or a view of the dispossessed state
或是被剝奪的國家這樣的一個觀點上面
Well, this is also the most basic thing we usually do for refugees.
那這也是我們一般對難民最基本的一個
know
認識
But the most interesting thing I think is in this kind of strength
可是最有趣的我覺得是在這種實力頭
He especially emphasized the matter of passports
他特別強調的是護照這個事情
These refugees are not without passports
這些難民不是沒有護照
It's that his old passport is no longer valid
而是他的舊的護照不再適用了
And when you don't have a passport
而且當你沒有護照之後
you no longer exist
你人就不存在了
So what is this reaction
那麼這個反應的是什麼呢
This reflects the fact that we are
這反映的是其實我們在
This social life is actually in a very realistic sense
這個社會生活其實在一個非常現實意義上面
we live in this society
我們在這個社會生活裡頭
Sometimes our credit cards and our ID cards are more important than our people
有時候我們的信用卡跟我們的身份證要比我們人還要重要
There was once such an example in the United States
在美國有曾經有這麼一個例子
one famous on the one hand at harvard
在哈佛大學一方面有名的一個
Not a professor in America a black professor
非一美國的這個教授一個黑人教授
Because of this, I can't get his ID on me at the moment.
就因為這個一時身上拿不出他的證件
by his this
被他的這個
It was the administrator of the residence who blocked the door.
就是住處的這個管理員擋在門外
It's ironic that the admin doesn't recognize his face
非常諷刺的是管理員不認得他的那張臉
I only recognize the ID he has on him.
只認得他身上有的那個證件
So for refugees
那麼對於難民來講
Do not have a certificate or a legal certificate
沒有擁有證件或是合法的證件
how to make him
如何生產 製造出他
Documents that allow him to move
能夠讓他移動的證件
become part of the whole refugee story
就成為整個難民故事當中
a very core key
一個很核心的關鍵
Although in our daily life
雖然這在我們的日常生活當中
may be a trivial thing
可能是一個微不足道的小事
If you don't have any documents, just go ahead and do it again.
沒有了證件 再去辦就好了
But when war comes
可是當戰爭來臨的時候
Documents may be the only thing that can prove you
證件可能是唯一能夠證明你
a material that still exists
還存在的一個材料
Then further I want to use such a
那麼進一步的我想透過這樣一個
simple expansion
簡單的展開
Let's think about our past few years
讓我們想一想我們這幾年來
In the past three to five years
就過去這三五年內
In fact, refugees are the international
其實難民正是國際上面
a huge huge issue
一個巨大的 巨大的議題
You can see these photos
這幾張照片大家可以看得到
In fact, I deliberately unselected
其實是我特意解選
as several
要作為幾個
several perspectives to understand
幾個視角來理解
so-called refugee status
所謂的難民的狀態
One perspective is of course the most famous one in the lower left corner
一個視角當然是最有名的左下角的這個
Fleeing from Syria
原來從敘利亞逃難出來
on this beach in greece
在希臘的這個海灘上面
This little sea that fell dead over there
倒在那邊死亡的這個小海
Then also because of this photo
那麼也因為這張照片使得
Syria's Refugee Crisis
敘利亞的這個難民危機
Gaining great attention in the European Union
在歐盟境內獲得極大的關注
It also makes this Greece slowly unfold
也使得這個希臘慢慢的展開
including the refugee camp
包括涉事難民營
Then more such an action of humanitarian relief
然後更多的人道救援的這樣的一個行動
This picture in the lower right corner
在右下角的這張圖
what we can see is
我們看得到的是
It turned out to be changed
原來有換
We can see that it's actually a boat
我們可以看得到其實是船
And it's a boat full of people
而且是塞滿了人的船
If you remember the so-called
如果各位還記得早年的這個所謂的
Our Memory of Vietnamese Refugees
我們對於越南難民的這個記憶
so-called boat people
所謂的船民
Probably such an image
大概就是這麼樣的一個形象
And the funniest thing is this
而最有趣的是這個
This group doesn't just stuff the boat
這一群人不僅僅是塞滿了船
and in
而且在
How to say
怎麼說
not just on board
不僅僅是在船上
on a boat full of people
是在一個塞滿了人的一個船上
Seeking this place to dock in the middle of the ocean
在汪洋當中尋求靠岸的這個地方
So in flight or in flight there is death
所以逃亡當中或說逃難當中有死亡
in danger while fleeing
在逃難當中有危難
what about when you arrive
那當你抵達了以後又怎麼樣
After arriving, in the upper right corner is a photo of the refugee camp
抵達了以後在右上角的是難民營的一張照片
then in the refugee camp
那麼在難民營裡頭
Actually these people live in tents
其實這些人住在帳篷裡面
Then it is very likely that these people are in our impression
然後很可能的這些人在我們的印象當中
The so-called refugees are also people with darker skin.
所謂的難民也是膚色比較黑的這些人
In fact, if you take a closer look at the ethnicity of Afghanistan
其實如果各位仔細看一看阿富汗的人種
or a false race
或者是虛假的人種
They may not all be so dark.
他們未必膚色都是這麼黑的
But in our current understanding and experience of refugees
但是在現在我們一般對於難民的認識跟經驗上面
I'm afraid it's the same as us for the so-called
恐怕也跟我們一般對於所謂的
Weak or poor countries are of the view that
弱勢國家或是貧窮國家的觀點是
or imagine being combined
或是想像是結合在一起的
So what I want to emphasize in these photos is
那麼這幾張照片我特別要強調的是
This is a group photo with no faces
這個是看不見臉的一個群體照
This is a reality that can be seen as miserable or tragic
這個是看得見悲慘或悲劇的一個現實
And this one is actually the one on the right, which may be the Naiming we most often see or may meet
而這一個其實已經右邊這個可能才是我們最常見到或可能遇見的奈明
But it's often the people we can't see
可是往往是我們看不見的這些人
Either they live in the camp far away from us
要麼他們住在營區裡頭跟我們距離很遠
Or they might just hang out with us
要麼他們可能就混跡在我們的身邊
But it never occurred to us that they might come from somewhere else
可是我們從來沒有想過他們可能是從別的地方來
Or we might recognize them from somewhere else
或者說我們可能會認得他們是從別的地方來的
But we don't understand what his past and experience are
但是我們並不理解他的過去跟經驗是什麼
Then this goes into, for example, the experience of Naiming.
那這就進入到譬如說關於奈明的經驗裡面
probably a lot about narrating this thing
可能有很多是關於敘述這件事情
How to tell Namin's story so that they can be accepted
怎麼樣敘述奈明的故事使得他們能夠獲得被接納的可能
How to describe his own experience so that his trauma can be alleviated
怎麼樣敘述自己的經驗使得他的創傷能夠被扶貧
How do you describe your experience so that you can meet the requirements of the International Rescue Agency?
怎麼樣敘述自己的經驗使得自己能夠符合那個國際救難總署
the required image and be able to obtain certain assistance
所要求的形象而能夠獲得一定的輔助
These are actually stories from Naiming’s experience
這些其實都是在奈明經驗當中故事
plays a very important role
所扮演一個非常重要的作用
exactly like his politics
恰恰如他的政見一樣
OK
OK
So simply a little bit in this
所以簡單稍微在這個
This is for refugees under the context of the United Nations
聯合國脈絡下面對於難民的這個
Judgment or specification to do a simple combing
判定或是規範做一個簡單的梳理
Then we go into
然後我們再進入到
in other stories
其他的故事裡頭
On the left is this so-called 1948
在左手邊是1948年的這個所謂的
human rights convention
人權公約
then at the beginning
那麼在一開頭
In fact, what I want to emphasize is probably that
其實我要強調的大概就是說
We all agree that human rights are a
我們都認為人權是一個
human beings are born
人類與生俱來
In this convention, the specification is as follows
在這個公約裡頭這個規範是這樣
It is an inherent dignity
它是一個inherent dignity
man as man
就是人作為人
A kind of dignity that should have or will have
本來就應該有或就會有的一種尊嚴
and is one that cannot
以及是一個不能
are equal
是彼此平等
And it is an inalienable right
而且是不能被剝奪的這個權利
As long as you are a member of human society
只要你是人類社會的一員
you have these things
你就擁有這些東西
What about this thing?
那它這個東西呢是
about liberty about justice about one of the most basic foundations of world peace
關於自由 關於正義 關於世界和平的一個最基本的基礎
I'll put one like this in a moment about the so-called refugee status
待會我會把這樣的一個對於所謂的難民身份
And these discussions about these so-called freedoms and military exercises that they surround refugees so-called derived from
以及關於他們圍繞的難民所謂衍生出來這些所謂的自由權利跟軍演的這些討論
give a more in-depth explanation
做一個比較深入的解釋
But for now let's just walk through a simple illustration like this
但是在目前我們就稍微先走過這樣的一個簡單的說明
Then he said that in this so-called
然後他說在這個所謂的
at the end
在最後
The last part he said
最後這個部分他說
If people don't want to be forced to have other
如果人們不想要被迫擁有其他的
Forced to resort to measures as a last resort to rebel against oppression and hegemony
被迫採取手段 最後的手段來反叛壓迫跟霸權的話
Then human rights must be protected through legal norms
那麼人權就必須要透過法律的規範來保護
This is referred to in the Human Rights Convention
這是人權公約提到
Why human rights matter because
為什麼人權重要是因為
If people don't want these people
人們如果不希望這些人們
take a violent and drastic action
採取一個暴力跟激烈的動作
to overthrow the government
來推翻政府
If you come to protest, to carry out acts of violence,
來抗議 來進行暴力行為的話
Then we need to protect the human rights of these people
那我們就有需要對這些人的人權進行保護
I think there is a hidden
這裡頭我覺得隱含了一個
A paradox in the relationship between the state and the people
國家跟人民之間關係的一種吊詭
This is when we talk about human rights today
這也是我們今天在談人權的時候
A subject that is often likely to be encountered first
往往可能會首先遭遇到的一個課題
but i'll come back here later
但我待會兒再回來這裡
on the right is
在右手邊的是
In 1951, the United Nations Refugee Agency formulated
1951年聯合國難民署制定
Regarding these treaties related to this so-called refugee
關於這個所謂難民相關的這些條約
Well here is a
那麼在這裡是一個
A definition of the word refugee
對於難民這個詞的一個定義
What did he call a refugee?
他說什麼叫難民呢
In addition to the above is to want to be in these specific time points
除了上面這個是想在這些特定時間點當中
Those who are recognized as refugees are other than refugees
被認定為難民的這些人是難民之外
There is also an expanded definition in the second clause below
還有一個擴大的定義是在下面這個第二條
that is
就是說
if they were
如果他們是被
If they have concerns about being
如果他們具有擔心被
because of their race, religion, nationality
因為他們的種族宗教國籍
or the identity of a particular social group
或者是特定社會群體的身份
or his political opinions
或者是他的政治意見
And if you have fear or worry about being oppressed or persecuted
而有被壓迫或是迫害的恐懼或擔心的話
Or leave his own country
或者是說離開了他自己的國家
or other than nationality
或國籍之外
or there is no way because of fear
或是沒有辦法因為恐懼的關係
or unwilling to allow themselves to be protected by the state
或是不願意讓自己受到國家的保護
And left the place where he used to live
而離開了他原來生存的地方
These people seek elsewhere
這些人到另外的地方尋求
seek settlement opportunities
尋求安居的機會
in such a situation
在這樣的狀況當中
These people can be called refugees
這些人就可以稱之為難民
because they can't
因為他們不能夠
Because they are unable or unwilling to return to their country of origin
因為不能夠或是不願意回到他們原來的國家
Well, to put it simply, what needs to be emphasized here is probably that
那麼簡單講在這裡特別要強調的大概就是說
The Difference Between So-Called Immigrants and Refugees
所謂的移民跟難民的一個差別
Immigration means you can come back after you leave
移民是你走了還可以再回來
A refugee is when you leave and don't come back
難民是你走了然後回不來
Then here we can see
那在這裡頭我們就可以看得到
to a certain kind of refugee or immigrant
到某一種難民跟移民當中
In fact, there is a relationship that overlaps but differs
其實有疊合卻又區別的一個關係
So here's a quick look at
那麼在這裡很快的讓大家看一下
In the past few years, in the relevant statistics of the United Nations refugee category
這幾年來在聯合國難民屬相關統計的
the real situation of some refugees
一些難民的實況
For example, in the world
比方講在全世界範圍當中
The forcibly displaced population has reached
被迫流離的人口達到了
I'm not good at math
我的數學不大好
This should be about 89 million yuan
這應該是八千九百萬元左右
that's a very, very high number
這是非常非常高的一個數字
then the next
然後下一張
For example in this
比方講在這個
Among the so-called low- and middle-income countries
在所謂的中低收入的這些國家當中
they refugees
他們難民
83% of low- and middle-income countries
中低收入國家當中的83%
In fact, they have become places for these refugees.
其實都成了這些收留難民的地方
Then there are 72% of refugees
然後有72%的難民
In fact, he was taken in in a neighboring country.
其實是在他的臨近的國家被收留的
or temporarily stopped
或是被暫時停留的
And then let's say in Verenea which is a very special case
然後比方講在維瑞內亞這是一個非常特殊的例子
One out of every six is ​​actually a refugee
其中有就是每六個當中有一個人其實就成為了難民
Then stay on a small island in South America like Aruba, the so-called China Travel Island.
然後收留在這個阿魯巴這個所謂的中旅島這樣的一個南美洲的一個小島上面
And what surprised me the most is that a country like Türkiye
然後最讓我意外的是土耳其這麼一個國家
A country that may not seem particularly advanced to us actually hosts 3.8 million refugees
在我們看起來可能不是特別先進的國家其實收留了380萬的難民
This is also a very astonishing number
這也是一個非常驚人的數字
Then every year, for example, there are 1.4 million refugee applications in the United States to become refugees
然後每一年譬如說在美國有140萬的這個難民的申請要成為難民
To become a refugee is not enough to say that I am a refugee, you have to apply and be recognized and accepted
要成為難民還不是說我是難民就可以了你要申請然後被認可跟接受
Then, of course, I think the world on the right is very interesting.
然後當然就是說我覺得右邊這個世界非常有趣的
Or should I say something very important
或者說應該講說非常重要的這個
very important one this
非常重要的一個這個
The numbers mean that among the world's population
數字就是說在世界的人口當中
Children make up 30%
孩童占了30%
But among these forced displaced
但是在被迫的流離的這些人當中
41% of the population is children
孩童的人口占了41%
So you can imagine that among these displaced people
所以你可以想見說在被迫流離的這些人當中
most of nearly half of
有大部分的 將近一半的
actually a minor
其實是未成年的小孩
ok
ok
These data are just for everyone to understand
那這些數據只是想讓大家理解到
That is to say, from the data
就是說從數據上面來看
Refugees are a very real
難民是一個很真實
And this problem that is happening
而且正在發生的這個問題
And the refugee problem is a big one
而難民問題一個很大的
facing several difficulties
面臨幾個困境
one of course is to say
一個當然就是說
Do you want to accept refugees?
有難民的你要不要收
Do you want to accept it, how to accept it, how to choose or not to choose
要不要收 怎麼收 怎麼選擇或不選擇
If you don't let them all in
那如果不讓他們都進來
Then how to arrange these people
那怎麼樣安置這些人
after settling down
安置下來以後
what happens to these people
這些人會發生什麼樣的事情
how long will this placement take
這安置的時間要多久
How to solve the problem of refugees
如何能夠解決難民的問題
In today's Europe and America
在今天的歐洲跟美國
It's actually a huge debate.
其實是一個非常巨大的一個辯論
especially in europe
特別在歐洲
Then I can discuss this in detail later.
那這個我待會可以再做細部的這個討論
So let's move on to the topic of refugees
那麼進入到難民的這個課題
Especially in the context of our East Asia
特別是在我們東亞的這個語境裡頭
There are probably two parts that I particularly want to mention
我特別想提到的大概是兩個部分
One is what is the reason for the movement of refugees
一個就是說難民的移動的原因是什麼
why do these refugees show up
為什麼這些難民會出現
The second is the relationship between refugees and the history of our place
第二個是難民跟我們這個地方的歷史中間
Is there any clear and specific relationship?
有沒有什麼樣比較明確跟具體的關係
For example, from the history of the Vietnam War
從比如說拿越戰這個歷史來看
Obviously, including in Syria or in Afghanistan
很明顯的就是包括在敘利亞或是在阿富汗都是如此
War is actually one of the reasons for the large number of refugees
戰爭其實是造成難民很大的一個原因
Of course, there are other
當然出史之外還有其他的
Including Tianhou, this change in climate
包括天后啦 氣候的這個變化
Also, for example, hunger
還有比如說飢餓
We'll probably mention this later
待會我們大概會提到的這個
This example from North Korea
北韓的這個例子
In fact, a lot of it is related to hunger.
其實很大部分是跟飢餓相關的
But politics is also an important factor
但政治也是一個很重要的因素
What's more interesting is that
更有趣的其實是
What happens when refugees appear because of the war?
當難民因為戰爭出現以後呢
The rescue of refugees is only related to the existence of the base
對於難民的救援只是跟基地的存在
There is a certain connection
又有一定的接合
For example, the photo on the right
比方講在右邊的這個照片
It's actually in this place in San Diego, USA.
其實就是在美國聖地亞哥的這個地方
There is one called Campandleton
有一個叫做Campandleton
It's actually a Marine Corps base.
其實就是海軍陸戰隊的基地
And in 1975 the outskirts of the base
而在1975年這個基地的外圍
Just set up the refugee forest below
就設置了下面的這個難民林
As a facility to receive these refugees from Taonan, Vietnam
作為接收從越南淘南出來的這些難民的這個設施
That is, here we can see
也就是說在這裡我們可以看到
The movement of refugees is actually the same as the movement of the military
難民的移動其實跟軍事的移動
It has a state that cooperates with or intersects with each other
它有一個相互配合或是相互交叉的一個狀態
as if we just thought of
就好像我們剛剛想到了
For example, in the experience of Afghanistan
譬如說在阿富汗的這個經驗裡面
These refugees actually just left on a U.S. military plane.
這些難民其實恰恰是搭著美軍飛機離開的
So at this time, let us think of a question
那麼所以這個時候就讓我們想起一個問題
So what is the relationship between these military interventions and humanitarian assistance?
那麼到底這些軍事介入跟人道救援的關係是什麼
Then these refugees who were rescued
然後被救援的這些難民
or accepted refugees
或是被接受的這些難民
Are they enemies or allies?
他們究竟是敵人還是盟軍
Are you a foreigner or a compatriot?
是外人還是同胞
Then this is the only one in Vietnam
那這個在這個越南一的
These refugees speak from the experience of immigrants in the United States
這些難民跟移民在美國的經驗來講
so strong
特別強烈的是如此
Because after the fall of Saigon in 1975
因為75年西貢淪陷之後
refugees coming to america
難民來到美國
In the hearts of many Americans
在很多的美國民眾的這個心裡頭
refugees from vietnam
這些從越南來的難民
and most likely their enemies
還很可能的是他們的敵人
But the reason why these people can come to the United States
可是這些人之所以能夠來到美國
Precisely because they used to be in the U.S. military
恰恰是因為他們曾經是在美軍
Be their ally in Vietnam time
在越南的時間成為他們的盟友
or their translator
或是他們的翻譯官
Or their other places that match these
或是他們的其他的地方上面配合的這些
Or simply put, these South Vietnamese regimes
或簡單講就是南越政權的這些
person
人士
They had the opportunity to come to Vietnam
他們才有了機會來到了越南
sorry for coming to america
對不起來到了美國
So in this sense
所以在這個意義上面
All refugee movements are related to the military
所有的難民的移動跟軍事的關係
In fact, it is worth our deep thinking
其實值得我們去深思
It's also worth thinking about
也值得我們去想一想
For the identity of those who move
對於這些移動的人的身份
In fact, it often follows us
其實也往往跟著我們
Judgments about politics are relevant
對於政治的判斷是相關的
further in Taiwan
進一步的在台灣呢
what is our own experience with refugees
我們自己對於難民的經驗是什麼呢
In fact, not long ago, this documentary was screened on official business
其實前不久才有一個在公事上面放映的這個紀錄片
It is said that there is a Jiangmei camp in Baisha, Penghu.
講的就是在澎湖白沙這個地方有一個蔣美營區
Once in 1978 to 1988
曾經在1978年到88年
It is a refugee camp received as this so-called Vietnamese descendant refugees
就是作為這個所謂的越南傳民難民接收的一個難民營
Well, this Jiangmei camp is actually
那麼這個蔣美營區其實
This is the original
原來也是這個
It is also the army or the camp where the army is stationed nearby
也是軍隊或者他附近也是軍隊駐紮的這個營區
So again we see this relationship between a military and this refugee camp
所以再次的我們看到一個軍事跟這個難民營的這個關係
But what's more, it's
可是更進一步的其實是
The existence of this camp is actually in our memory
這個營區的存在其實在我們的記憶當中
In fact, especially for young people, they may never have thought of such a thing.
其實特別對於年輕人可能是從來沒有想過有這麼一回事的
So this director Liu Jixiong and his team
那麼所以這個導演劉吉雄跟他的團隊
In fact, it took a lot of effort to rearrange and introduce such a history
其實花了很大的功夫重新去整理跟介紹這樣的一個歷史
allows us to see that in 1975
使得我們可以看到在1975年
After the fall of Vietnam in 1975
1975年越南淪陷之後
In fact, Taiwan is also participating in the entire anti-communist camp.
台灣其實也參與在整個反共陣營當中
played a humanitarian role
扮演了一個人道救援的角色
Although not particularly prominent
雖然不是特別的突出
But it's also part of our history
但是這也是我們的歷史的一部分
But it is often not remembered
可是卻是往往不大去記得的
It is very interesting that in these coming to Taiwan these
非常有趣的是在這些來到台灣的這些
Vietnamese refugees
越南難民
Actually there are some good parts
其實有好一些部分
In fact, the so-called Chinese
其實是所謂的華人
So this involves the whole of this guy in Vietnam
那麼這又牽涉到了整個在越南的這個人
this so-called
這個所謂的
Vietnam’s socialist identity actually includes Chinese
越南的主義身份裡頭其實又有華人的
Chinese are also a very important presence
華人也是一個非常重要的存在
And the Chinese are also in this process
而華人也在這個過程當中
Come to Taiwan or even stay
來到台灣甚至留下來
Of course a large part also
當然有好大一部分也
Passed through Taiwan to other places
通過了台灣到了其他的地方去
So this batch
所以這一批
Refugee compatriots in the atmosphere of the times at that time
難民同胞在當時那樣的一個時代氛圍當中
Are they treated as refugees or as compatriots?
是被當成的難民還是被當成的同胞
Or possessed person or own person
或是附身人還是自己人
They are refugees surviving in the dry sea
他們是枯海求生的難民
Still regardless of some for the sake of freedom and democracy
還是不顧一些為了自由民主
And the anti-communist consciousness that came to Taiwan
而來到台灣的反共意識
Then I ask these few questions
那我透過這幾個提問
In fact, I keep wanting to outline
其實不斷的想要去勾勒的
Probably through the refugees
大概是透過難民的這個
stories and history
故事跟歷史
how to rethink
怎麼樣重新去思考
in this through the refugees
在透過難民的這個
Nearby we can see
鄰近當中我們可以看到
Political, military and humanitarian assistance
政治軍事跟人道救援當中
very complicated relationship
很複雜的一些關係
that soon i want to pass
那很快的我想透過
A few stories from North Korea
北韓的幾個故事來
talk to you further
跟大家進一步的講
This so-called refugee
這個所謂的難民的
The relationship between refugees and stories
難民跟故事的關係
Let's put it this way
這麼說吧
I chose these three works
我選擇了這三個作品
I won't go into specific details
我不會特別的細部的談
but i think it's worth it
但是我覺得很值得
Let me explain to you a little bit
稍微跟大家說明一下
This one on the left is called Puyanmei
在左手邊這個叫做普顏美
Actually
其實是
If you are on facebook
各位如果在臉書上面的話
or easily found on Google
或在Google上面很容易可以找到
his photo
他的照片
Because he published such a book
因為他出了這麼一本
In order to live this book
In order to live這個書呢
Also has translation in Chinese
在中文也有翻譯
And then translated many other languages
然後也翻譯了很多其他的語言
It has been followed up and several books have been published.
它後續了也出了好幾本
The book is basically one of its own as a North Korean refugee
這個書基本上是它作為一個北韓難民的一個
So-called
所謂的
Testimonial A Testimonial and Narrative
Tesimonial 一個見證跟敘事
So
那麼
Of course it now puts
那當然它現在把
what should i say
應該怎麼說的
that is
就是說
This testimony and narrative speaks for itself
這個見證跟敘事談的是它自己的
such an experience
這樣的一個經驗
Then in the middle this one is a
那麼在中間這一本是一個
Korean-American writer named Chris Lee
韓裔美國作家叫Chris Lee
Wrote a novel written in 2013
寫了在2013年寫的一本小說
叫做 How I Became a North Korean
叫做 How I Became a North Korean
that's how i became a north korean
就是我怎麼成為一個北韓人
This part of the novel is about
小說的這個內容談的是
On the border between China and North Korea
在中國跟北韓的邊境
this we now understand
這個我們現在理解到
It is the serious emergency on the China-North Korea border
就是中朝邊境有這個嚴急事
Then strictly border this ethnic knowledge area
然後嚴邊這個民族知識區
such a space
這樣的一個空間
In fact, there were many in the 90s
其實有很多在90年代
There are many North Korean refugees
有很多的北韓難民
From North Korea to China
從北韓來到了中國
so so this story
那麼所以這個故事
It was in such a 90's
就是在這樣的一個90年代
North Korean refugees North Korean refugees to China in the background
北韓難民 朝鮮難民到中國的背景當中
to talk about a Korean in China
去談一個在中國的朝鮮族
Actually went to America
其實去了美國
And then back to the border between China and North Korea
然後又回到了中朝邊境當中
saw or encountered these refugees
見到了或是碰到了這些難民
And because of China's opportunity
而自己因為中華的機遇
Also considered part of the refugees
也被當成的是難民的一部分
So How I Became North Korean
所以How I Became North Korean
It's actually about showing an immigrant turned refugee.
其實是要去呈現一個移民變成難民
Such an interesting but complicated relationship
這樣的一個很有趣但是很複雜的一個關係
Then the novel on the right is a translation of
那麼在右邊這一小說是一個翻譯的
It was originally a novel written by a Korean writer in Korean
就是本來是韓國作家用韓文寫的一個小說
then translated into english
然後翻譯成為英文
It's called I met...
叫做I met...
Can't see Beauty now
現在看不到Beauty
I met Loki on Loki
I met Loki on Loki
It’s just that Beauty is very simple, that is, I met a person like Logic Magic
就是Beauty很簡單就是我遇到了邏輯幻這樣一個人
Logical fantasy is actually in this story
邏輯幻其實是在這個故事裡頭
The refugee who didn't show up until the very end
一直到最後最後才出現的那個難民
But this story...
可是這個故事...
The protagonist is actually a journalist in Korea
主角其實是一個在韓國的新聞記者
He saw this one about logic sickness
他因為看到了這個關於邏輯患的一個
This is the introduction of Escape
就是逃難的這個介紹
And there is a touch to go after him
而有了一個觸動想要去追索他
What is the experience of being a refugee?
做一個難民的經驗是什麼
Then this probably has something to do with what happened to him in the story.
那這個大概也跟他自己在故事當中所發生的
Personal experience has an interesting contrast
個人的經驗有一個很有趣的對照
But I'll leave this part for now
但這個部分我暫時就先撇下
The reason why we talk about these three is because
那這所以談這三個是因為
One is the self-narration of the refugees themselves, right?
一個是難民本身的自我講述對不對
The other is through a very external perspective
另外一個是透過一個非常外在的視角
To imagine being on the border between China and North Korea
去想像在中朝邊境當中
Possible Refugee Opportunities and Correlations
可能的難民機遇跟相互關係
And the other one is actually a projection entirely at a distance.
然後另外一個其實是完全在一個遠方的投射
But through this projection he initiated a process of seeking refugees
可是透過這個投射他啟動了一個追尋難民的這個過程
one of these three stories
那這三個故事的一個
The juxtaposition actually presents an interesting
並列其實呈現了一個我覺得很有趣的
triangle structure
三角架構
that refugees are often in the story
那就是難民往往是在這個故事當中
Well
呃
Among all the refugee stories on the Internet
在網網關於所有難民故事當中
He is often the one who is forced to
他往往是那個被迫要
should say so
應該這麼說
He is often the one imagined
他往往是被想像的那個對象
But at the same time he was placed in a specific position
可是同時他又被放在一個特定的位置上面
to express refugees
來表達難民
I'm not very clear about this
我這個講的不是很清楚
I simply put it this way
我簡單的這麼說就是說
as a refugee
作為一個難民
He was actually expected to tell a story about him
他其實被期待了去講述一個關於他的故事
And the story that is expected to be told
而這個被期待所講述的故事
has his script
有他一定的劇本
For example we will see later
比方講我們待會看到
here it will be
在這裡就會
I skip here first
我先跳過這裡
It's clearer here
在這裡就比較清楚
For example, the author Pu Yanmei is a North Korean defector
譬如說作者普言美是一位脫北者
also a human rights fighter
也是一位人權鬥士
his story is
他的故事是讓人
His story brings people together
他的故事讓人得以一潰就近
Behind the Iron Curtain regime in North Korea
北韓的鐵幕政權背後
The life of ordinary people
普通人民生活樣貌
This is a video of him and his family trying to escape North Korea
這是一段他與家人為了逃避北韓
Overcoming the pressure of freezing
跨越冰凍的壓力
Will escape the clutches of ex-pats and gangsters
將逃出前客跟黑幫的魔掌
Into the Gobi Desert to Mongolia
走進戈壁沙漠抵達蒙古
Defector's story on the flight to South Korea
在飛往南韓的脫北故事
If you read the introduction of such a book
各位如果看這樣一個書的介紹
you will find wow
你會發現哇
it's simply a
這簡直是一個
an adventure story isn't it
一個冒險故事 不是嗎
then this adventure story
那麼這個冒險故事
It is actually going to outline
它其實是要去勾勒
such a thrilling escape
這麼一個逃難的驚險
So so included here
那麼所以包括在這裡的
English is partly actually
英文是 部分其實是
An illustrated direction of the beginning of its story
它故事的一開始的一個說明方向
In the first paragraph it says
在第一段它說
On the cold black night of March 31st
On the cold black night of March 31st
at
就在
This March 31, 2007
2007年的這個3月31號
such a cold night
這麼一個寒冷的黑夜
my mother and me
我的母親跟我呢
This squats very low
這個 蹲得非常低
Then press the green river
然後在壓綠江
this frozen green river
這個冰凍的壓綠江的這個
crawling along the coast
沿岸當中不斷的爬行
This presses the green river to separate
這個壓綠江分別的
North Korea and China
北朝鮮跟這個中國兩邊
Well here are a lot of
那麼在這裡有很多的
Patrol guards in
巡邏守衛在
above and below us
在我們的上面跟下面
and then these
然後呢這些
These guards will be here
這些守衛會這個在
per white foot
每白尺的
Sorry, what is the name of every two in Chinese?
對不起 每一二中文叫什麼
scold each other for nothing
罵 對 每白罵
There will be these guards in this episode
這個劇集當中就會有這些守衛
Then
然後
there will be soldiers and they say
會有士兵 然後他們說
anytime to those involved in crossing the border
隨時到涉及通過邊界的這些人
so so we don't know what's going to happen
那麼所以我們不知道會發生什麼事情
We just want to leave North Korea and go to China in a positive way or in a very extreme way
我們只是積極茫茫的或是非常極限的想要離開朝鮮到中國那裡
we might have a chance to survive
我們也許會有一個機會能夠生存下來
The story of Napu Yanmei tells a very typical
那普顏美的這個故事講的是一個非常典型的
We're almost a typical refugee
我們幾乎可以這麼說是一個難民的典型
In fact, this typical refugee image also reflects the image of refugees.
這個難民的典型其實也把難民的形象
The story about refugees is placed in an almost stereotypical position
跟關於難民的故事給放在了一個幾乎是刻板印象的這個位置
As a refugee, he must go through a lot of risks
作為難民他必然經過非常大的兼險
As a refugee he must have gone through all sorts of brutality
作為難民他一定經過了各種的殘暴
as a refugee he must be
作為難民他一定如何如何如何
OK
OK
Well, if you think about it, you will know
那各位只要想一想就知道說
The millions of refugees we just saw
千千萬的難民我們剛剛看到的
In fact, not all have the same experience
其實未必都經過相同的經驗
In other words, everyone's experience cannot be compared with pain.
或者說每一個人的這個經歷跟痛苦也都不能夠類比
OK
OK
Well, but we need or say that among these solemn
那麼可是我們卻需要或說在這些正嚴當中
but often as a reading
卻常常作為閱讀來說
Perhaps more of what we are consuming is the suffering and experience of these people
可能更多的我們在消費的是這些人的苦難跟經驗
as one of our wonders
作為我們的某一種奇觀
So through this spectacle we inspired a
於是透過這個奇觀我們啟發了一種
A kind of sympathy for the suffering of refugees
對於難民的苦難的一種同情
Well, of course this is to a certain extent
那這個當然在一定程度上面
Not necessarily a bad thing, right?
不見得是一件壞事 對不對
because we can see
因為我們可以看到了
In fact, we also have such an experience in our hearts.
我們內心其實也對這樣的一個經驗
It is possible to have a heart of silhouette
是可以有一種側影之心的
And not because it's from, say, North Korea
而不會因為它是比方講是朝鮮來的
rather different
而有所不同
But here I think a very interesting question is
可是這裡我覺得一個很有趣的問題就是
Will we because it's because of North Korea
我們會不會因為它是因為朝鮮來的
And think differently about such refugees
而對於這樣的難民有不同的想法
Will we because of today's refugee
我們會不會因為今天這個難民
is from Syria or Afghanistan
是來自於敘利亞或阿富汗
and think differently
而有不同的想法
I'm not asking this question as an answer
我把這個問題拋出來不是作為一個答案
but a question
而是一個問題
Actually let's think about it
其實讓大家去想一想
When we're dealing with refugee stories and refugee status
當我們在面對難民故事跟難民身份的時候
Do we have some inherited ideas and concepts
我們是不是有一些繼承的想法跟觀念
These things are exactly what I hope through today's speech
那這些東西恰恰是我希望透過今天的這個演講
able to propose
能夠提出
I brought it up to think with everyone
提出來跟大家一起思考的
ok then let's move on to this
好 然後我們接著再看這個
How it Became North Korean
How it Became North Korean
This is also in Guardian
這個也是在Guardian
One of the British Guardian newspapers for this book
英國的衛報上面對於這個書的一個
brief introduction
簡單的介紹
let's take a look
我們快讓大家看一下
Most of these North Korean defectors
大部分北韓的這些脫北者
We are in Chinese and we have a term called defector
我們就在中文我們有一個名詞叫脫北者
or this rebel of politics
或者就是政治的這個反叛者
They came to North Korea where they left
他們來到他們離開的朝鮮
North Korea leaving via China
通過中國離開的朝鮮
At any given time
At any given time
anytime
就任何時候呢
There would be thousands of these refugees here
就會這裡都有上千的這些難民
hiding in this state of living in hiding
躲在生活在一種躲藏的這個狀態當中
Scared they might be caught and deported
很害怕他們可能會被抓到跟遣返
Women may be trafficked into this
女性可能會被這個販賣成為
The so-called new workers or married people
所謂新工作者或者是被嫁人
These Chinese farmers who can't get wives
這些不能夠娶不到老婆的這些中國的農夫
Then men may be violently oppressed by this gangster and become a special park
那麼男性可能會被這個黑幫勢力暴力壓迫成為專場的公園
These teachers of the church, these teachers of the Jesuits may also
那教會的這些教師 耶穌會的這些教師也可能會
Why, no matter what, they may come to aid and resettle these refugees
為 怎麼講 也可能會來援助跟安置這些逃難者
But sometimes, they are treated as criminals.
但是有時候呢 也會把他們當成了犯人
even force them to read the bible and ask them to change their religion
甚至要強迫他們閱讀聖經 要求他們用改變他們的宗教信仰
in exchange for their freedom, or their loyalty to the country
來交換他們的自由 或是他們對國家的忠誠
So he said this novel, he is among several different narrators
所以他說這個小說呢 他在幾個不同的這個敘事者當中
Make an exchange where the male lead is called Yongju
做一個交換 其中的男主角叫做Yongju
He's a kid who was supposed to be a high ranking North Korean general.
他是一個本來是高階北韓將領的小孩
Then because of this
然後因為父親母親被的這個
Killed for political reasons
政治的緣故被殺害了
So he and his mother fled
所以他跟母親就逃難
and my sister escaped
還有妹妹就逃難
During this escape
在這個逃難過程當中
Mom and sister are lost
媽媽跟妹妹都失散了
He's left alone at the Chinese border
就剩下他一個人在中國邊境
stay above
上面留了下來
Then the other one is called Johnny
那麼另外這個叫Johnny
is a female
是一個女性
Then she was pregnant before fleeing.
那麼是逃難之前就已經懷孕了
so you can see
所以可以看得到
Just before this description
剛剛前面這個描述
This part about this so called sex trafficking
關於這個所謂的性交易的這個部分
Maybe it's related to Johnny's story
可能就是跟Johnny的故事相關
Then there is another fact that
然後還有一個實際就是說
the one we were talking about
我們剛剛要說的一個
originally grew up on the edge
本來在沿邊長大
then went to America
然後去了美國
back to the edge
又再回到了沿邊
During this experience
在這個經驗過程當中
Accidentally mistaken for a North Korean
不小心被當成了北韓人的
Such a person is called Danny
這樣一個這個人叫Danny
so so i think this story is very interesting
那麼所以我覺得這個故事非常有趣
He sees through this Danny's point of view
他透過這個Danny的視角
let's see say
讓我們看到說
when you don't have a passport
當你沒有護照的時候
when you have no documents to prove
當你沒有證件可以證明
who are you when
你是誰的時候
in the Sino-Korean border
在中朝邊境當中
you are likely to be treated as
你就很可能會被當成
One who fled North Korea
一個逃離朝鮮的這個
Then this as a
那這個作為一個
is highly risky
是有高度風險
OK
OK
Then the only salvation is in this story
那麼唯一的解救在這個故事裡頭
The only salvation is through this assistance of the Church
唯一的解救是透過教會的這個協助
And the church has become another
而教會又成為了另外一種
Another form of coercion for this institution
另外一種脅迫的這個機構
they may threaten you
他們可能會威脅你
if you don't listen
如果你不聽話的話
hand you over to the police
把你交給警察
Or like this unit report in the locality, etc.
或是像地方的這個單位報告等等
Then this is the description in the story
那這是在故事裡頭這些描述
Then I think these descriptions are also
那我想這些描述也是
Based on my understanding and research
就我的了解跟研究
there are also some
也是有一些
basic
基本的
Sometimes the writer actually did some research and investigation
有時候這個作家其實是透過了一些研究跟考察
wrote such a story
寫出了這樣的一個故事
Then this story shows us another
那這個故事展現了一個我們另外
This one from Taonan in front of this one
在這個前面的淘南的這個
Beyond the template and the typical
樣板跟典型之外
What is less noticed is that
比較少注意到的其實是
A dialectical relationship between the seekers of the South and the rescuers
淘南者跟解救者之間的一種辯證關係
And the core of this story is that Danny became the hero who saved everyone
以及在這個故事裡頭最核心的就是Danny成為解救了大家的那個英雄
And why does he have such an ability
而為什麼他具有這樣的一個能力
He actually grew up on the edge of a rock
他其實在岩邊長大的
So he also has a family background that can help
所以他還有一個家族的背景能夠幫忙
He recovers his identity in the process of fleeing
他在這個逃難的過程當中恢復他的身份
At the same time, he also rescued his fellow sufferers
同時也把他的一同的難友解救出來
I think the last story is also very interesting.
最後這個故事我覺得也特別的有意思
I'll introduce you soon
很快的跟大家介紹一下
In fact, it is about such a person as Locking One.
其實講的就是這麼一個Locking One這個人
He is also a North Korean defector
他是也是北韓的脫北者
then in this story
然後在這個故事裡頭
I didn't describe how he defected from North Korea
我沒有描述他脫北的經過
Just simply stating that he has experienced difficulties from scratch
只是簡單的說明他經歷了從頭的困難
came to belgium
來到了比利時
He came to Belgium without knowing a word of French
來到比利時的他不懂一句法語
I don't know how to live in this place
也不知道這個地方該怎麼生活
He only has a few hundred euros in cash
他只有手上幾百塊歐元的現金
must live every day of his stay in belgium
必須度過他在比利時的每一天
through for this
透過對於這個
It is in this story that the heroine
就是在這個故事裡面這個女主學
North Korean defector's recourse for this refugee
對於這個難民的北韓脫北者的追索
he experienced again
他重新經驗了
This North Korean defector was in a Belgian
這個脫北者在比利時當時的一個
each step for example
每一個步驟比方講
How to get to the hotel where he stepped down at the time
怎麼樣去到他的當時下踏的旅館
To face those who may have been for this refugee at that time
去面對那些當時可能對於這個難民
Those who are not very polite in the interaction
互動當中有所不大禮貌的這些
The hotel staff
旅館的這些工作人員
how to face the possibility
怎麼樣去面對可能
It's not the people who really bullied him back then.
其實不是當時真正欺負他的那些人
But in his experience
可是在他的經驗當中
those who are very sure
那些非常把握的
Very self-sustaining these European whites
非常自己維持的這些歐洲白人
Interacting with Asians
跟亞洲人的互動
So in my opinion the story
那麼在我看來這個故事裡面
actually put the story
其實把這個故事
In fact, using refugees as a figure
其實把難民作為一個figure
a clue
一個線索
His clue allows readers as well as writers
他這個線索讓讀者以及作家
Be able to recount experiences that a refugee might have encountered
能夠重述一個難民可能遭遇的經驗
while putting yourself in
而同時把自己放在
in that experience
在那個經驗裡面
in this sense
在這意義上面
He and the one in front
他跟前面那個
I became North Korean
I became North Korean
a little bit like
有一點點類似
In fact, we are all asking us to put ourselves
其實都是要我們把自己
plunge into that refugee experience
投身在那個難民經驗當中
then in this sense
那麼在這意義上面
he left
他離開了
he left on the one hand
他一方面離開了
This so-called third-person description
這個所謂第三人稱的描述
also left a first-person
也離開了一個第一人稱的這種
The so-called subjective refugee
所謂主觀的難民的這種
spectacle self-narrative
奇觀式的自我敘述
Instead, it creates a
而反而創造出了一個
reflective space
反思性的空間
let's think about it
讓我們去想想
How to tell refugee stories
怎麼樣講難民的故事
to be able to tell the stories of refugees
才能夠把難民的故事
Three-dimensional
講得立體
Speak well
講得
To be able to make the refugee experience
才能夠讓難民的經驗
not just as a
不是僅僅的作為一個
to be consumed
被消費的踏著
but one that can help us
而是一個可以幫助我們
such a possibility of self-reflection
反思自我的這樣的一個可能性
So in this story
所以在這個故事裡頭
there is a very classic
有一個非常經典
very important in my opinion
在我看來非常重要
and a part of the classic
而且經典的一個部分
That's Loki 1 in Belgium
那就是Loki 1在比利時
ended up staying very successfully
最終非常成功地留了下來
So I won't expand on the details of the head.
所以頭的細節我就不展開了
but what about after this stay
但這留下來以後呢
he is attending
他在參加
Working in a restaurant, I met a guy from the Philippines
在餐廳打工認識了一個從菲律賓來的
illegal immigrant
也是非法移民
That's because of this illegal immigrant woman from the Philippines
那因為這位從菲律賓來的非法移民女性
don't speak french
不會講法語
So he always wanted to go to an English-speaking country
所以他一直希望能夠去到一個講英語的國家
After Lokkawang met her
Lokkawang認識她了以後
The two of them are actually just this colleague in the restaurant
兩個人其實只是在餐廳的這個同事
But the application for a long time
但是日久申請
So when this girl decides to go to England
所以當這個女生決定要去英國的時候
Lokkawang is also disregarding himself
Lokkawang也這個分不顧身的
Willing to follow her to England
願意追隨她去英國
So for the heroine of the story, the narrator,
那麼對於故事的這個女主角這個敘述者來說
He thought it was an unimaginable thing
他覺得這是一個不可想像的一個事情
He had a hard time getting out of his refugee status.
他好不容易才脫離了他的難民身份
why is he willing to let go
為什麼他願意放下了
The chance to finally get settled in this Belgium
最終能夠獲得安居的這個比利時的機會
And once again became a refugee and ran to
而再次的成為難民跑到
Or at least an illegal immigrant to the UK?
或是起碼是非法移民跑到英國去呢
In the course of this pursuit, he discovered that
那在這個追索過程當中他發現
it's actually really easy
其實很簡單
Because in their step by step
因為在他們一步一腳印的
in the process of creating your own life
打造自己的生活的過程當中
They're no longer the subsidized, doled out refugee
他們不再是那個接受資助的 接受救濟的難民
In the process of no longer being self-reliant and self-reliant
在不再在自立自強的這個過程當中
These refugees have their own dignity
這些難民有了自己的尊嚴
He knows he can live like everyone else
他知道他也可以跟其他人一樣生活
Learning another language is hard work
學習另外一個語言 雖然辛苦
Adapting to another environment is not easy
適應另外一個環境 雖然很不容易
But this provides an opportunity for them to strengthen themselves
但是這提供了一個他們自強的這個機會
So so I want to pass through these few stories
那麼所以我想透過這幾個故事
What I want to outline is probably such a simple thing
我想要去勾勒的大概是這麼一個簡單的事情
that's what we know about refugees
那就是我們對於難民的認識
cannot just stay at one
不能夠僅僅停留在一個
In the relationship between the recipient and the sympathizer
這個接受者跟同情者這樣的一個關係當中
At the same time, our experience with refugees cannot only be
同時我們跟難民的經驗也不能僅僅的
treat it as outside this visible window
把它視為在這個可見的視窗之外的
such an invisible being
那樣的一個不可見的存在
They are likely to be around in our daily life
他們很可能就在我們的日常生活周邊
maybe as we know these
也許就像我們所知道的這些
The so-called migrant workers from Southeast Asia are also good
所謂的東南亞移工也好
or the previous
或者是前面的
others from different places
其他來自於不同地方
These moving crowds of different cultures are also good
不同文化的這些移動的人群也好
Not necessarily in our extreme vision
未必在我們極觀的視野
But they are equally important
可是他們一樣是重要的存在
They are also fighting for their freedom and dignity.
同樣也在爭取著他們的自由權利跟尊嚴
Soon I will provide a little bit of good context
很快的我提供一點點小好的脈絡
Let everyone understand why North Korean Namin is in my discussion
讓大家理解為什麼北韓奈民在我的討論當中
play a relatively important role
扮演一個相對重要的地位
On the one hand, if you still remember the numbers I mentioned earlier,
一方面如果各位還記得我前面講的數字
Stories about the Vietnam War
關於越戰的故事
In fact, the whole Vietnam War story is an anti-Communist story
其實整個越戰的故事就是一個反共的故事
if we can
如果我們可以這麼
A slightly rough word for understanding
略為粗暴的一個理解的話
So so today we are imagining
那麼所以在今天我們在想像
when North Korea or North Korea
北朝鮮或是北韓的時候
In fact, the supporters of North Korea are often placed in a
其實北韓的託北者也往往被放在一個
To understand from the anti-communist narrative
反共敘事當中來理解
These people turn north means they are against Kim Jong Un's regime
這些人託北意味著他們反對金正恩的政權
Against such a state of North Korea
反對北韓的這樣的一個狀態
The freedom they fought for was in a larger sense
他們爭取的自由在更大意義上面
It affirms the value of democracy and freedom
是肯定一種民主跟自由的價值
But if you look closely at these people
可是如果你細細觀看這些人
The experience of these North Koreans who came to South Korea
這些託北者來到了南韓的經驗
When you come to experience in different places
來到不同地方的經驗的時候
you realize
你就發覺
that democracy and freedom
那個民主跟自由
In fact, it is not as tolerant as imagined
其實並不如想像的寬容
Actually asked these people
其實要求了這些人
conform to a particular image
服應某一種特定的形象
provide a specific function
跟提供某一種特定的功能
No matter what we talked about in the early years
不管是我們早年講的
An imagination of anti-communist consciousness
反共意識這樣的一個想像
Or today we talk about North Korean defectors
或者是今天我們談脫北者
or some other attempt at such expression
或是其他的這種表述的一種嘗試
In fact, to a certain extent
其實都在一定程度上面
Otherize this so-called refugee
把這個所謂的難民他者化
Othering means
他者化的意思就是說
There is actually a distance between you and me
你跟我其實是有距離的
I can see you so much
極令我看得見你
But that distance exists
但是那個距離是存在的
of course here
那當然這裡就
So to simplify the context of this detail
所以簡單一點這個細節的脈絡
That is to say, during the period from 1994 to 1998
就是說在1994年到1998年期間
In fact, there was a big famine in North Korea
在北韓其實發生了一個很大的災荒
Then in this frenzied state
那在這個激荒的這個狀態當中
Many people left North Korea
很多人就離開了這個北韓
Then this departure is for North Korea
那這個離開是對於北朝鮮的這些
For the people before 1994
人民來說在1994年之前
Before a big move
行程大的移動之前
Actually, it's not a serious matter for them.
其實對他們來講並不是一個很嚴重的事情
Because the border between China and North Korea is not so tight
因為中朝的邊境並不是那麼緊繃的
a state of strict
嚴守的一個狀態
Many residents in North Korea
很多的在北韓的居民
probably during the cultural revolution
可能在文革時期
It happened to be the one who fled from the border to North Korea
恰恰是從沿邊逃到了北韓區的
So these groups where a lot of people trade across the border
那麼在很多人進行邊境貿易的這些群體
It may also be in the process of border
也可能在邊境的過程當中
form a so-called cross-border group
形成一個所謂的跨境的群體
Not to mention the so-called Koreans along the border
更不要說在沿邊的所謂的朝鮮族
In fact, in a long historical context, in the rainy environment of Northeast Asia
其實在一個較長的歷史脈絡在東北亞的雨境裡頭
In fact, there are many cross-border mobile
其實有很多的跨境的移動
So it's actually the border that separates the two sides.
所以其實是邊界分離了這兩邊
In other words, the state system actually separates the people living on the border
也就是說國家這個體制其實分離了在邊境上面生活的人民
Then in the context of the 1990s
那麼在90年代的這樣的一個脈絡裡頭
Those who escaped from North Korea
這些從北韓逃出來的人
In many cases, it will be regarded as a so-called economic immigrant.
很多時候就會被當成是所謂的經濟移民
But in China there is no way to recognize them as economic immigrants
但是在中國是沒有辦法承認他們作為經濟移民的
Because there is actually a treaty of friendship between China and North Korea
因為在中國跟朝鮮之間其實有一個友好的條約
What this treaty subsequently stipulates or requires is
這個條約以後規定的是或說要求的是
China should not be concerned about the stability of this regime in North Korea
中國不應該對朝鮮的這個政權的穩定性
pose any threat
形成任何的威脅
So if China accepts these fleeing refugees as economic immigrants
那因此如果中國接受了這些逃難的難民作為經濟移民
To some extent, the above is the opposite.
某個程度上面就反向的說明了
The political situation and economic instability in North Korea
在朝鮮的這個政局跟經濟上面的不穩定
As a result, possible conflicts between the two countries
而形成了兩國可能的居無跟衝突
Then it is also impossible for him to admit that they are so-called defectors
那麼同樣的他也不可能承認他們是所謂的defector
is to defect from North Korea
就是脫北
politics
政治
the rebellion
叛亂
not a rebellion
不是叛亂
meaning in politics
就是政治上面的意義者
Because it also shows that China may become accommodating North Korea
因為這也顯示了中國可能變成是接納北朝鮮
a space of meaning molecules
意義分子的一個空間
So in this sense
所以在這個意義上面
Whether it's a North Korean defector
不管是脫北者也好
It doesn't matter if it's meaningful
不管是意義者也好
whether economic refugees
不管是經濟難民
economic migrants or refugees
經濟移民或是難民也好
These different identities
這幾個不同的身份
In fact, it is impossible to know exactly
其實都不能夠確切的掌握
and explain a dilemma and experience they encountered
跟說明他們所遭遇到的一個困境跟經驗
That's why
那也是因為這個樣子
So we need to compare a
所以我們需要在對這樣的一個
The concept of immigration and this imagination are further investigated
移民這個概念跟這個想像做更進一步的考察
Those few stories help us build a simple context
那這幾個故事幫助我們建立了一個簡單的脈絡
This is what I was probably just trying to say
這個是我大概剛剛試圖要說的
After 2000
2000年以後
because of the tightening of border controls
因為邊境管制的緊縮
so that also changed the policy
所以那還改變了政策
Also reject North Korean defectors from South Korea
也拒絕了脫北者以往南韓
So some defectors
所以有部分的脫北者
In fact, through China
其實也就通過了中國
maybe to thailand
可能到了泰國去
Then I went back and forth to Europe and the United States
然後輾轉的再去到歐洲跟美國
then this brings us to
那這就讓我們想到
Among the problems of survival and freedom in disasters and politics
在災難跟政治當中生存跟自由這些問題當中
It might just be a formal number
恰恰可能是形數了
or outline a state of refugee existence
或勾勒的難民存在的一個狀態
That also reminds us
那這也讓我們想到
The whole is in the rainy environment of East Asia
整個在東亞的雨境裡頭
Whether it's civil war
不管是內戰也好
Whether it is the Cold War or not, it is actually a situation that has not completely ended.
冷戰也好 其實都是沒有完全的結束的一個情形
So after defecting from North Korea, Po Yeon Mi had a saying
所以脫北之後 普演美有一個說法
He said why he left
他說為什麼離開 簡單講
just want to live like a human
就只是想活得像人一樣
Then this imagination of wanting to live like a human being
那這個想要活得像一個人這樣的一個想像
Back to a discussion about human rights
回到一個關於人權的討論裡頭
Let us see a couple of very complex paradoxes
就讓我們看到了幾個非常複雜的悖論
For example, where do the human rights of refugees come from?
比方講 難民的人權從何而來
If we go back to these conventions
如果我們回到前面講的這些公約
stipulated in the convention
公約上有規定
But these provisions of the convention
可是公約上的這些規定
Which unit is there to implement, realize and guarantee?
有哪一個單位來執行跟實現跟保障呢
So Hanna two rounds in the 1940s
所以漢納二輪在1940年代
In these notes written in the 1950s
在50年代寫的這些註作裡頭
In fact, we are constantly discussing this issue about human rights.
其實就不斷的在討論這個關於人權
the issue of citizenship
跟公民權的這個問題
from his point of view
從他的角度來說
without citizenship
如果沒有公民權
In fact, it is almost equal to no human rights
其實幾乎就等於沒有人權
Because you don't have a country to provide your human rights protection
因為你沒有一個國家提供你的人權保障
Human rights are actually the very people who are deprived of human rights
人權其實是恰恰被剝奪的人權的人
the one that was attached
才被附有的一個
imagined political rights
想像的政治權利
So if we go back to the whole political practice of refugee movement
那如果我們回到整個難民移動的政治實踐裡頭
It is often seen that a situation like this occurs
往往也可以看到類似這樣的一個狀況出現
That is to say, when he has no way to obtain any local acceptance and status
也就是說當他沒有辦法取得任何在地的接納跟身份的時候
These people are excluded
這些人就被排據在外
Whether it's cast adrift at sea
不管是拋流在海上
or simply be resisted or shut down in this
或是簡單的就是被抗拒或關閉在這個
Beyond this so-called barbed wire
這個所謂的鐵絲網之外
So Allen said that this Paradise is
所以阿倫說這個Paradise就是
after you lose your human rights
你失去了人權之後
This makes the issue of human rights a key
才使得這個人權的問題變成了一個關鍵
so what
那麼怎麼樣
how about this from citizen
從公民的這個怎麼樣
through the protection of citizens to make these people
透過公民的保護使得這些人
have access to the same human rights protections
也能夠獲得相同的人權保護
become an important starting point for the entire human rights discussion
就變成整個人權討論很重要的一個出發點
But this is only one end of the human rights debate
可是這僅僅是關於人權討論的一端
I skip here a little bit
這裡我稍微跳過
come back later
待會再回來
Also recently on the sidelines of the human rights debate
最近也是人權討論的一端
Because from another French sociologist
因為從另外一個法國的社學家
From Huang Siye's point of view
黃思葉的角度來講
The idea of ​​talking about human rights
所謂談人權的想法
In fact, it is a process of political consultation
其實它是一種政治協商的過程
It is precisely because these people have no human rights
就是正是因為這些人沒有人權
But you admit that they are human
可是你又承認他們是人
So human rights have become a topic worthy of everyone's concern and discussion
於是人權變成了一個值得大家來關心跟討論的話題
So that means when we discuss human rights
那麼也就是說當我們討論人權的時候
In fact, we are comparing the human problem with the mobile problem and the refugee problem
其實我們是把人的問題跟移動的問題跟難民的問題
Put it on a political god
放到了一個政治異神上面來
Here we can directly think of
那這裡我們可以很直接的想到
For example, think about Hong Kong, which we supported very much a while ago
比方想前一陣子我們非常支持的香港
Many Hongkongers want to come and stay
很多香港人想要來想要留下來
Whether you can stay or not is actually a lot of questions here.
能不能留下來其實在這裡有很多的問題
It's not that we verbally
不是說我們表面上口頭上面
Conscious support for them
意識上面的支持他們
we can easily hijack them
我們就能夠很容易的劫拿他們
This involves the revision of the presidential decree
在這裡頭牽涉到了總統法令的修改
to all kinds of national borders and national political imagination
到種種的關於國家邊界跟國家政治想像
these topics
這些話題
Those things are actually
那這些東西其實都
view throughout the
觀設在整個對於
Our current imagination of politics
在當前我們對於政治的想像
above this question
的這個問題上面
are very closely related to
有很密切的關於
So Hong Siye said
所以洪思葉說
There is a saying that is
有一個這麼說法就是
These refugees fighting for human rights
這些在爭取人權的難民
or wait for human rights
或是等待人權
Humanitarian Refugees
人道救援的難民
In fact, in the whole social community
其實是在整個這個社會社群當中的
no share
無份之份
It's just that they don't actually have such a share
就是他們其實沒有這麼一份
But what?
可是呢
It is precisely this lack
恰恰是缺乏了的這一份
is that we are worth discussing and working hard
就是我們值得透過討論跟努力
to make it up
去把它補上的
That's also in a sense
那這也在某個意義上面
pushes us to imagine
推動了我們去想像
In the context of Taiwan
在台灣這個語境裡頭
to imagine the existence
去想像那名存在
or that name
或是那名法
such a
這樣的一個
A possible advance on the law
法則上面的一個推進的可能
Do we have such a tolerance
我們有沒有這樣的一個寬容
is there such a one
有沒有這樣的一個
willing to accept one's own mind
願納一己的胸襟
to receive those who might come into our territory
來接納可能來到我們境內的
these refugees
這些難民
Today we are almost
在今天我們幾乎
This issue is not discussed in this society
在這個社會上面不討論這個問題
Surprisingly
很意外的是
In fact, we also have such a meaning of accepting refugees.
我們其實也有這麼一個接納難民的意思
If you go back to Peng Hu's story about the Meiying area,
如果各位回到彭胡講美營區的故事裡頭的話
then today we will
那麼今天我們會
what can we do
我們能夠怎麼樣
participate in the international community for these
參與到國際社會對於這些
People who drift and suffer in the world
在世界上漂流跟受苦的人
Offer some of our possible assistance
提供一些我們可能的援助
Where are our formal conditions and our legal conditions
我們的正式條件跟我們的法律條件在哪裡
This may be our further
這或許是我們進一步
worthy of discussion in this society
值得在這個社會裡頭展開的討論
then time is limited
那麼時間的有限
I'm going back a little bit quickly to two snippets
我很快地稍微回到兩個片段
I especially want to emphasize
我特別要強調
Especially in these two segments
特別在這兩個片段裡頭
Wanting to repeat the further misfortune is
想要重複跟在進一步慘勢的是
In fact, for refugees
其實對於難民來講
the situation they live in
他們所生活的這個處境當中
What we can see is
我們可以看得到的是
language and writing
語言跟書寫
In fact, it is a very important ability
其實是非常重要的一個能力
with the condition
跟條件
because it's about whether they can be seen
因為這關乎於他們能不能被看見
so many refugee stories
所以很多的難民故事
in a certain sense
在一定意義上面
Although there is such a book market
雖然有這麼一個書籍市場
These needs for spectacle
需要奇觀化的這些需求
but a larger part
可是更大的一個部分
record keeping
也在於記錄跟保有
The experience and experience of these people
這些人曾經的經驗跟經歷
So that is to say
也因此就是說
we can't just blame the book market
我們不能僅僅的去責怪書籍市場
may want specific marketing
可能會想要特定的行銷
For example, a type like Puyanmei
譬如說普演美這樣的一種
image
形象
or put all these
或者是說把所有的這些
The refugee experience has become a
難民的經驗都變成一種
Very orientalized story
非常東方奇觀化的故事
At the same time beyond such a critique
同時在這樣的一個批判之外
we should also see
我們也應該去看到
behind these stories
這些故事背後
the moods it wants to record
它所要記錄的那些心情
follow the sound
跟聲音
Because these sounds may just be
因為這些聲音恰恰可能是
a possibility that they can be heard
他們能夠被聽見的一個可能性
Back to Erlan
回到二蘭
When Erlan was discussing that there were too many refugees
二蘭在討論有太難民的時候
there is a very
有一個非常
self-deprecating
自嘲的這樣
Or a statement like Synical
或者說Synical這樣的一個說法
He said what refugees need most
他說難民最需要的是什麼呢
What refugees need most is people's livelihood
難民最需要的其實就是民生
what kind of livelihood
什麼樣的民生呢
What kind of livelihood is good
什麼樣的民生都好
as long as you can make trouble
只要你能夠鬧事
able to be seen
能夠被看見
then you have a chance for power
那麼你就有爭取權力的機會
Think about it, everyone
各位想想
In fact, in our society
其實在我們這個社會裡面
in today's world
在今天的這個世界裡頭
probably a lot of the time
可能很多時候恰是如此
those who can't be heard
那些沒有辦法被聽見
with those who can't be seen
跟沒有辦法被看見的那些人
Or the crowd is actually not recognized by us
或人群其實也就不被我們
remember and understand
記得跟理解了
So so language and story
那麼所以語言跟故事
ID, diary, write these things
證件 日記 書寫這些東西
i think it might be in
我想可能是在
researching refugee stories
研究難民故事當中
An action that is particularly worthy of our concern
特別值得我們去關懷的一種行動
From this point of view
從這個角度來講
all
所有的
or in my understanding of
或在我的理解的
so-called literary studies
所謂的文學研究
or cultural studies
或文化研究來說
It's not just closed doors
其實都不僅僅是關著門
Only read novels and stories
只看小說跟故事
is a consumer behavior
都是的一種消費性行為
It's actually all one
它其實都是一個
Our one conduit to the world
我們連接世界的一個管道
That is to say
也就是說
If we have any connection with the world
如果我們跟這個世界有任何聯繫的關係的話
What we often have to ask is our connection with the world
那我們常常要問的是我們跟這個世界的聯繫
where did it come from
究竟從何而來
Where do we start our relationship with the world?
我們是從哪些地方展開跟這個世界的關係的
I am borrowing, for example, one from Teacher Qian Yongxiang
我在借用譬如說千永祥老師的一個
i think he has a
我覺得他有一個
It's an interesting question, he said
很有趣的一個問法他說
Especially when talking about cross-strait relations, he said
特別談到兩岸關係的時候他說到
People of their generation may not know
他們這一輩的人各位也許不知道
Teacher Qian Yongxiang
千永祥老師
Also in the Institute
也在研究院
A retired professor at this human center
這個人設中心的一個退休教授
retired researcher then he is this
退休研究員那麼他是這個
contact ideas
聯繫思想
an editor in chief of this publication
這個刊物的一個主編
He actually cared for so long
那麼長時間他其實很關懷
The interaction between the two sides of the strait, especially the exchange of ideas
兩岸之間的這個互動特別是在思想的這個往來
So he said that in their generation, he was probably
那麼所以他說他們這一輩他大概是
the 50s
50年代
Born in the late 40s and 50s
40年代末50年代出生
This so-called
這一輩的這個所謂的
people of this generation
這一代的人
He said that in their interactions with mainland Chinese people
他說他們跟中國大陸人士的互動當中
There is this care of a modern China
有一個現代中國的這個關懷
That is to say, for them, communication between the two sides of the strait
就是說兩岸溝通當中對他們來講
Talking about modern China is a common language for each other
談現代中國是彼此的共通語言
or shared care
或是共同關懷
But our generation
可是我們這一輩
Or the generation later than us
或是比我們更晚的這一輩
When communicating with the mainland
跟大陸的往來的時候
what is our connection
我們的關聯是什麼
our relationship today
我們的關聯在今天
Probably Rising China, right?
可能是崛起中國 對吧
Maybe it's a Chinese threat or something
可能是中國威脅或等等的
So from a conversation like this
所以從他這樣的一個談話
What I'm actually going to expand on is that
我其實要去展開的就是說
not the point is not to say
不是問題的關鍵不在於說
Are we already in the world
我們是不是已經在世界裡頭
Or do we lack an international outlook
或說我們是不是缺乏國際觀
No further connection to the world etc.
沒有跟世界有進一步的聯繫等等
The point is that
關鍵是在於
How do we connect with the world
我們是怎麼樣跟世界發生聯繫的
i think the president's reading
我覺得總統的閱讀
different novels and stories
不同的小說跟故事
In fact, it provides exactly one
其實恰恰提供的是一個
a way to bring us into the world
把我們帶進世界的一個方法
I feel special in this
在這一上面我覺得特別的
how to say
怎麼說呢
Thanks to myself for being able to work in such an academic field of literature
感謝跟自己能夠在這樣的一個文學的學術領域裡頭
to grow and develop
去成長跟發展
because it really drives me some
因為它確實帶動了我一些
Opportunities that may not exist in other fields
在其他領域可能不會有的機會
And these opportunities are actually some of our different channels to the world.
而這些機會其實下是我們通往世界的一些不同的管道
So today on this occasion I can share these discussions with you
所以今天在這個場合能夠跟大家分享這些討論
Actually a big expectation
其實很大的一個期待
In fact, I hope that the friends here
其實是希望讓在座的朋友
In addition to understanding what a researcher's research colleagues are doing
除了理解研究員的研究同仁在做些什麼之外
Also think about the ways in which we can interact with the world
也能夠想一想我們能夠跟世界交往的方式有哪些
What topics and topics are worthy of our development and concern?
有哪些的課題跟話題是值得我們去展開跟關懷的
From this we can reconstruct
從這個當中我們可以重新建構
even develop a Taiwan society that is different from the past
甚至是發展一個不同於以往的台灣社會
and the relationship between Taiwanese society and the world
以及台灣社會跟世界的關係
Then I think it's almost time to talk about this place today
那我想時間也差不多就今天講到這個地方
If you say something bad, please include more
說得不好的地方還請大家多多的包含
Thank you very much Vice President Huang and
那非常感謝黃副院長以及
Dean Wang Qin's family members and friends present
王秦院長的家屬以及在座的朋友
very happy to have this opportunity today
非常高興今天有這個機會
I can meet you here
能夠在這邊跟大家相遇
thank you all
謝謝大家
this we thank you for this
這個我們謝謝這個
Professor Wang's explanation of this
王教授的解說這個
Real Refugees and Refugees Presented in Literature
真實的難民跟文學所呈現的難民
The relationship between the two is of course very complicated
這兩者之間的關係當然是非常的複雜
There are thousands of threads in this intricate relationship
有千絲萬里的這個錯綜的關係
I think everyone must have different questions in their minds.
我想大家心中有一定各自有不同的疑問
want to ask questions
想提問
So I think we're going to open it up to the audience right now.
那我想我們現在就開放給各位聽眾
to ask questions
來提問問題
then we have a good one
那我們好好有一個
Do you want to explain the small gift?
小禮物要不要說明一下
We have a quota of 10 small gifts
我們有10個小禮物的名額
That's an alcohol bottle, although the epidemic has slowed down
那是一個酒精瓶雖然那個疫情已經趨緩
But this may take a while so we'll
但是這可能還要跟大家一陣子所以我們就
Give everyone a souvenir made by Academia Sinica
送大家酒精瓶中央研究院做的一個紀念品
Thanks
謝謝
yes
是呀
now please everyone
那現在就請大家
speak up
踴躍發言
Hold your hand, this gentleman raises his hand first
這把握著手好這位先生先舉手
Please say
請說
Send the day first
先送日子
then come join the army just aired
然後來加入軍隊剛好放送
i see them
我看到他們
At the beginning they also knew that there was a shortage
剛開始他們也知道很缺
Medicine, in March last year
藥啊去年3月的時候
full drug shortage
全缺藥缺
food
糧食啊
That's when they were all pitiful
就是他們都很可憐那時候
The east belt lacks everything
東帶什麼都缺
In the end, the Taiwan government was always missing, and they didn't forget about us.
到最後台灣政府都是有缺過來他們也沒忘記我們
In this way, after joining the army, give me the Taiwan flag
這樣然後加入軍隊之後台灣國旗給我
I think
我覺得
impossible
不可能的
Would you like to stand in the middle
你要不要站到中間來
Because you are the protagonist under this brow light
因為你是這個眉光燈下面的主角
Thank you very much for sharing this friend
非常謝謝這位朋友的分享
Indeed, I think we are actually on this matter in Ukraine
確實我覺得我們其實在烏克蘭的這個事情上面
But it should be said
不過應該這麼說了
I think Taiwanese society has
我覺得台灣社會在近年來
This desire and imagination for participation in the international community
對於國際社會的參與的這個慾望跟想像
desire, will and ability
慾望意願跟能力
In fact, it is much stronger than before
其實比以前都要來得強烈許多
Glad to be there to actually visit
很高興在現場有到實際去參觀
See this friend who Naiming helped
看過奈明提供過協助的這個朋友
I probably think
我大概想
if stretched a bit
如果做一點延伸的話
What I'm trying to say is probably
我大概想說的大概就是說
Our Contact with Naiming
我們跟奈明的接觸
Including myself, I didn't actually have any real contact with Naiming.
包括我自己其實沒有跟奈明有實質的接觸
so i can't say
所以我不好說
what should we say
我們應該怎麼樣這樣的一個話
But from the context of a literary study
可是從一個文學研究的脈絡裡頭
In fact, what keeps reminding ourselves is an ethical issue
其實不斷的在提醒我們自己的是一種倫理上面的問題
That is, in the context of this contact
也就是在這個接觸的脈絡當中
what was their response
他們的回應是什麼
what is our attitude
我們的態度是什麼
And are there any other expectations that interfere with this relationship?
以及在這個交往當中的有沒有其他的這些預期干擾了
In fact, it may be a very simple relationship of mutual assistance and assistance.
其實可能是一個非常單純的一種互助跟協助的關係
Then when I understand that means
那麼當我明白就是說
A lot of international aid today is in the context of Taiwan
今天很多的國際援助在台灣的語境裡頭
There is such a need to see Taiwan or the expectation of Taiwan Can help
有很有這種需要看見台灣或是台灣Can help這樣的一個期待
Then I think it's understandable, and it's what we've been doing for so many years.
那我覺得這也無可厚非也是我們這麼多年來
The accumulated political, cultural, and economic power
所累積的這些政治、文化、經濟實力
An opportunity worthy of international exposure
值得在國際上展現的一個機會
But what I keep thinking about is probably
但是我想不斷的在想的大概就是說
Then, are there some ethical issues that may be deeper in this, and we will think about it later?
那這裡頭有沒有一些可能更深層的這些倫理問題之後我們去思考
Then I just throw this question out for everyone
那我只是把這個問題拋出來提供給大家
and no further criticisms or thoughts on this
並沒有其他進一步的這個批評或者是想法
I also hope to take this opportunity to hear more about your experiences and ideas.
也特別希望能夠在這個機會多聽聽大家的一些經驗跟想法
That's because our central research
那因為我們中央研究
Because Ukraine has accepted many Ukrainian refugees since the war
因為這個烏克蘭這個戰爭以來也接納了不少烏克蘭的難民
Not to mention some compatriots from Hong Kong like this
那更不用說從香港過來的一些這個同胞這樣
So this is a process where you can see a lot of hard work.
所以這個都是可以看到很多很辛苦取折的過程
Well, we're actually lucky too.
那我們事實上也是很幸運
This hope does not become a refugee
這個希望不要成為難民
that other
那其他的
This woman is fine, let's start with a woman
這個女性好了我們先來一個女性
one man one woman one man one woman
一男一女一男一女
Hello teacher, I am a student of the Institute of Literature
老師您好我是文學所的學生
is also a nonfiction writer
也是一個非虛構的寫作者
Then I focus on the topic of "Tibetans in Exile"
然後我關注的議題是在《流亡藏人》的這一塊
Then I just heard the teacher say
那我剛剛聽到老師您說
Do you think language and writing are very important
您覺得語言跟書寫是非常重要的一件事情
because need to be seen
因為需要被看見
I agree with this
這個我很同意
Well, I have a small question,
那可是我有一個小小的疑問是
Because the "Exile" we are in contact with
因為我們在接觸的《流亡者》
In the process of telling the story, in fact
敘述故事的過程裡面其實
found out that one thing is
發現到一件事情是
In fact, the so-called traumatic memory
其實所謂的創傷記憶
They are likely to be in the present moment of memory preservation
他們很有可能在記憶的保存的當下
because it hurts
因為太痛苦了
So they have to do the preservation in a twisted way
所以他們必須要用扭曲的方式來做保存
which is very likely what we recorded
也就是很有可能我們記錄到的
the story we heard was
我們聽到的故事是
There will be this truth of truth and falsity of the story
會有故事的真偽的這個真理性存在
that being a writer is because a recorder
那身為一個書寫者是因為一個記錄者
what do you think teacher
老師您是怎麼看
but we have to write we have to say
但我們要寫我們要說
But I really have no way to verify the authenticity of the story
但是我真的沒有辦法驗證故事的真偽這件事情
thank you very much for your question
非常謝謝你的問題
It's really common
這確實是大家常見的
A common discussion on refugee issues
在難民問題上常見到的一個討論
For example, when a
比方講當一個
How about this refugee seeking asylum?
怎麼講 要尋求庇護的這個難民
The story he told, how do you verify that what he said is true?
說的故事 你怎麼樣去驗證他說的是真的
It's fake, it's included in the novel I just described
是假的 包括在我剛描述的這個小說裡頭
In fact, there is one, the third book
其實有一個 就是第三本
In fact, there is a very important plot is
其實有一個很重要的情節就是
He this Loki One when he came out
他 這個Loki One他出來的時候
In fact, no, I don't have any documents on me anymore.
其實沒有 身上已經沒有任何的證件
can prove who he is
可以證明他自己是誰
So he needs a third party to help him
所以他需要透過一個第三方來幫他
the process of doing a test or piece together a story
進行一個檢證或拼湊故事的這個過程
Therefore, in the process
也因此在這個過程當中
delayed the time he was able to obtain detention
拖延了他能夠取得拘留的這個時間
So the question you raised is a very crucial one.
那 所以你提的這個問題是一個非常關鍵的
one question but
一個問題 可是
Then this key issue will be in the field of practice
那這個關鍵的問題會在實踐的場域當中
Formation is sometimes a form for refugees
形成 有時候是形成對於難民的一個
Further make things difficult for example
進一步的刁難 比方講
Ask him to keep repeating the things he went through
要他不斷的重複他經過的那些事情
It can be a very painful experience for him
對他來說這可能是一個非常痛苦的經驗
or
或者是說
the truth of what he said
他所說的事情的真實性
make him helpless
使得他自己沒有辦法
make him feel that he is not only not accepted
使得他覺得他不僅是沒有被接納
Even being further questioned and suspected
甚至是被進一步的質疑跟懷疑
Then this may all be at the same scene
那這個都可能是在一個現場的
A key issue in ethics
倫理當中的一個很關鍵的問題
But another level of problem
可是另外一個層次的問題
is in this part of the story
是在故事的這個部分
Then this involves the process of writing the story.
那這就牽涉到說故事的寫作的過程當中
it is a collaboration
它是一個collaboration
For example, his narration was written down by another person
譬如說是他的講述另外一個人寫下來
Or he worked hard in his own way
還是他用他的方式很努力的
talk about his experience
把他的經驗說下來
But it may not be able to make everyone understand
可是未必能夠讓大家能夠看得懂
Or in other words, there are many of these
或者是說在這裡頭有許多的這些
very strange thing
很奇怪的東西
let me give you an example
比方講我舉一個例子
In this Campo-Le
在這個Campo-Le
It is the refugee experience in Cambodia
就是柬埔寨的這個難民經驗裡面
There is a saying that
有一個說法就是
One of the sayings circulating as this refugee experience is that
作為這個難民經驗流傳的一個說法就是
You have to plant a tree
You have to plant a tree
It has a saying that is
它有一個這個說法就是
you need to
你要把自己
planted like a tree
種下來像一棵樹一樣
That statement is incomprehensible to most people.
那這個說法對於大部分的人不理解
People in the veins will find it strange
在脈絡的人會覺得很奇怪
what is like a tree
什麼叫做像一棵樹一樣
So the explanation of these advances is that
那麼所以這幾進步的解釋就是說
The reason to be like a tree
之所以要像一棵樹一樣
it's because we're going to keep silent
是因為我們要保持沉默
we will continue to grow
我們要繼續的生長
But let's not touch the others
可是我們不要去觸碰其他的
Don't let our language oppress us
不要讓我們的語言形成了對我們的壓迫
Because during the process of fleeing in Cambodia,
因為在柬埔寨這個逃難的過程當中
Probably because of this, of course there are a lot of details
很可能會因為這個當然有很多的細節
I can't speak very clearly and clearly now.
我現在沒有辦法講得非常的清楚跟明白
but in simple terms
但簡單來說
If we plant this into a tree
如果我們把這個種一棵樹
If it is a metaphor for the escape experience
當成是一個逃難經驗的隱喻的話
In fact, the ability to read these metaphors when we need them
其實我們需要的時去閱讀這些隱喻的能力
Then this ability involves saying
那這個能力就牽涉到說
How do we contextualize the place where these metaphors take place
我們怎麼樣脈絡化這些隱喻發生的這個
How to provide the context of this pair of metaphors
怎麼樣提供這個對隱喻發生的這個脈絡
How to understand the context of these metaphors
怎麼樣理解這些隱喻發生的這個脈絡
in the course of history
在歷史過程當中
The meaning in this historical context
在這個歷史脈絡當中裡頭的意義
Then I think the most important possibility
那我覺得最關鍵的可能
Back to the question of authenticity
回到這個真偽的問題
The fact is that we should not simply doubt
其實還在於我們不要單純的懷疑
should say so
應該這麼說吧
Let's not be too obsessed with judgments of authenticity
我們不要太執著於真偽的判斷
because as an outsider
因為作為一個外在者來講
In fact, it is difficult for you to judge the authenticity
其實你很難判斷真偽
Right, if you're not the party
對吧 如果你不是當事人
if you haven't experienced
如果你沒有經歷過
If you have no other supporting materials
如果你沒有其他的材料的佐證
I'm afraid it's hard for you to judge
你恐怕在很難去判斷
Is this story true or false?
這個故事到底是真的還是假的
or in this story
或者說在這個故事裡面
is there any exaggeration
有沒有誇張的部分
But what we want to hear is
可是我們要聽到的是
Or what we're going to read is in
或者我們要讀到的是在
something beyond these rhetoric
這些修辭之外的那個東西
It doesn't matter if it's his heart
不管是他的心聲也好
Whether it's his trauma
不管是他的創傷也好
Whether it's some clues he wants to leave behind
不管是他想要留下來的一些線索也罷
I think this is as a
這個我覺得是作為一個
I think where we should pay attention
我覺得應該去關注的地方
instead of saying
而不是說
Because there's probably some exaggerated material here
因為這裡有可能是一些誇張的材料
So he cannot be further adopted
所以他就不能夠被進一步的採納
what i want to say is
我要說的是
so i care
所以我關心
stories about refugees
關於難民的這些故事
Actually, I just had a slideshow that didn't say anything in particular.
其實我剛剛有一個投影片沒有特別講的
That is, it is often a so-called future-tive history
就是它往往都是一個所謂的future-tive history
or future-tive documentation
或是future-tive documentation
The records of these stories are actually very fragmented.
就是這些故事的記錄其實都是非常的零碎的
It's all accidental in its retention
都是在它的保留都是很偶然的
So we actually need a lot of effort
所以我們其實需要很大的一個努力
To piece together these fragmentary and incomplete ingredients
去拼湊這些零碎的不完整的這個食料
And here we must run the risk of facing the real embarrassment
而在這裡我們必然冒著面對真為難變的這樣一個風險
So my advice would be to try to stay out of its sight
所以我的建議會是試圖在它的眼外
trying to read between the lines
試圖去理解它的眼外之意
Rather than just grasping the so-called truth
而不是僅僅的掌握著這個所謂真為的這樣的一個問題
this is my simple answer
這是我簡單的回答
ok sir
好,這位先生
Hello teacher, this thank you very wonderful
老師,你好,這謝謝非常精彩
And very, very responsible speeches
而且非常就是非常富有責力的演講
Usually in speeches I think of an issue like race in America
通常演講中我想到一個問題是像美國的種族問題
just like black people
就是像黑人他們
They played the role of black slaves to Delamin
他們當初對戴拉明國是黑奴的角色
So they're sort of a refugee.
所以他們某種程度也算是一種難民
They also spent a lot of effort to fight for freedom.
他們也是花了很多力氣爭取到自由
Then just know the racial inequality of black people now
然後就是只知道現在黑人在種族的不平等
Or socioeconomic inequality is still a very, very big problem
或是社會經濟的不平等還是一個非常非常大的問題
So I want to ask the teacher if
所以想請問老師有沒有
This is actually quite
就是這個其實是蠻
quite
蠻
I think it's pretty
我覺得是蠻
don't know how to solve
不知道該怎麼解決
That is, what kind of resettlement will refugees have in their new countries?
就是難民到新的國家裡面到底有什麼安置
how to make them follow
怎麼樣讓他們跟
how to make them better
怎麼讓他們變得比較好一點
Do you have any opinions or indirect shares from the young teachers?
從小青春老師有什麼看法或間接可以分享一下
ok thank you very much for this question
好非常謝謝你的這個問題
I'm afraid it's a bit beyond my ability
這恐怕有點超出我的能力範圍
Sounds like such a huge mission to save Kasen
聽起來像是要解救艙森的這麼一個巨大的任務
But I think it's fair to say that
但是我想可以說的大概是
racial issues
種族問題也好
Actually in this refugee story that I was trying to describe
其實在我剛試圖描述的這個難民故事裡面
In fact, there is a side
其實有一個側面就是
is the difference of identity
就是身份的差異
This difference in identity may be racial
這個身份的差異可能是種族的
probably an accent
可能是口音的
Maybe even today is a regional
甚至可能今天也是一個地域的
So it is not surprising that there are various differences in human society
那麼所以人的社會有各種各樣的差異並不奇怪
But the way we treat differences
可是我們對待差異的方式
But it often adopts a method of exclusion and violence
卻往往會採取一種排據跟暴力的方式
then this will be
那這個就會是
This should be our human society
這個就應該是我們這個人類社會
A question that should be constantly reflected on
應該不斷反省的一個問題
So back to that question about black people
那麼回到那個關於黑人的這個提問
Or this question from ethnic minorities
或是少數民族的這個提問
including the question of placement
包括那名安置的問題
Here I think there are two aspects worth considering
這裡頭我覺得有兩個面向值得去考慮
the first is
第一個就是
Talk about the problem of placement
講那名安置的問題
In fact, there is an angle to say
其實關有一個角度是說
how do we bring him in
我們怎麼樣把他納進來
So we, for example, through various
所以我們譬如說透過各種的
Funding e.g. speaking language courses
資助譬如說語言課程
send them to language courses
讓他們去上語言課程
so that they can quickly integrate into the society
使得他們可以很快的統化於這個社會
So in this sense
那麼因此在這個意義上面
We are expecting these names to be us
我們等於期待了這些那名成為我們
OK
OK
Then you should think about it
那各位應該去想一想就是說
We expect others to be us
我們會期待他者成為我們
it sounds like nothing is wrong
聽起來好像沒有什麼不對
right
對不對
Right
對吧
Do you think this is not possible? Shouldn’t it be?
大家會覺得這樣不可以嗎 不應該嗎
It doesn't sound like anything is wrong, does it?
好像聽起來沒有什麼不對 是不是
Since you came to our country, you should
你既然來到我們國家應該
when you're in Rome do what Romans do
when you're in Rome do what Romans do
When you come to Rome, you have to learn how the Romans live
來到羅馬要學著羅馬人的過生活
But for Naming
可是對於奈明來講
His coming may not be what he wants to come
他的到來可能不是他的願意到來的
He was accidentally
他是突然之間不小心
Or because of these accidents that he couldn't resist
或是因為他無可抗拒的這些意外
and came to this place
而來到了這個地方
then one
那麼一個
Police have a lot of help
警委有很多的協助
But such a request or expectation
可是那麼一個要求或是期待
he became what we imagined
他成為我們想像的那個
good no missiles
良好的 不會導彈的
Then the well-behaved and kind Nai Ming
然後乖巧的善良的奈明
Even Nai Min, who is very grateful
甚至是抱含了很大的感激的奈明
In fact, it is a big burden for him.
其實對他來講都是一個很大的負擔
So in the Naming study
所以在奈明研究裡頭
It should be said that in the critique of Naming studies
應該這麼說 在批判奈明研究裡頭
there is a big discussion
有一個很大的討論
In fact, for this debt
其實就是對於這個債務
It's just that Nai Ming has a feeling of apology
就是奈明懷有一種歉舊之情
This discussion because this debt reflects the
這個討論 因為這個債務反映的是
His freedom was actually given
他的自由其實是被給予的
His freedom is not what he fought for
他的自由其實不是他爭取來的
but because of these various external factors
而是因為這些種種的外部的因素
gave him such a free opportunity
給予了他這麼一個自由的機會
So he should survive
於是他應該倖存感期
This seems to be in line with our general social logic
這看起來是符合我們一般社會邏輯的
such an idea
這樣一個想法
But when you go back to the refugee experience and history
可是當你回到難民的經驗跟歷史
In the context of movement
跟移動的這個脈絡當中
you'll find that for them
你就會發現對他們來說
That's actually a bigger burden
那其實是一個更大的負擔
As a result, we encounter many so-called
也因此我們碰到很多的所謂的
This so-called immigrant group
這個所謂的移民群體
In fact, in the end, they are all regarded as people in this society.
其實最終都是被當成這個社會上的
problem group
問題群體
But that problem is like what we have today
但是那個問題就像我們今天
Facing the child in exile
面對放流般的小孩面對
so-called problem children
所謂的問題兒童
Maybe that's not the problem with these kids and children
可能那問題不在於這些小孩跟兒童身上
It is the society that treats these children
而在於這個社會對於這些兒童
with the child
跟小孩
face to face
面對跟
The expectations and requirements for them
對他們的這個期待跟要求
perhaps far beyond
或許遠遠超出了
their burden
他們的負擔
then this is what i think
那這個是我想
How to understand refugees
怎麼樣去理解難民
between the receiving country
跟接納國之間的
Acceptance of a complex relationship between societies
接納社會之間的一個複雜關係的一個
an ethical dimension
一個倫理面向
Then of course race is a thing I think
那麼種族當然是一個我覺得
The very core question here
在這裡頭很核心的問題
why are they required
為什麼對他們有所要求
because they're not like us
因為他們不像我們
so
所以
to eat pork like us
要像我們一樣吃豬肉
come here to do something like us
來了要像我們一樣做什麼什麼的
Well this is actually
那麼這個其實是
We don't see the context of their life
我們沒有看見他們本來的那個生活脈絡
What exactly is it
究竟是什麼
So I think treating the other back to Derrida this time I just
所以我覺得對待他者回到德里達這次我剛
Sorry for not being able to
很不好意思沒有能夠
expanded part
展開來的部分
When Derrida talked about Vietnam and Namibia
德里達談越納議題的時候
he was talking about a
他談的是一個
is an unconditional Vietnamese
是一個無條件的越納
It's that you can't ask him to do what he is
就是你不能夠要求他怎麼樣他就是
You have to take it as it is
You have to take it as it is
he is like that
他就是那個樣子
and accept him that way
然後接受他是那個樣子
so you can expand a
於是你才能夠展開一個
Comparing the above relationship with ethical significance
比較具有倫理意義上面的關係
otherwise
不然
will always be in a so-called
永遠會是在一個所謂的
This humanity gives and
這個人道給予跟
In this expected exchange relationship with this harmonious society
跟這種社會和諧的這種期待的交換關係裡面
This is probably what I learned from reading refugee stories
這個大概是我從閱讀難民故事跟
critical refugee studies
批判難民研究當中
One of the more important inspirations
獲得的一個比較重要的啟發
share with everyone
分享給大家
Please say
請說
yes
是
I am a family member
我是家屬
The family of Wang Shijie
那個王世傑家屬
I study economics and AI
我是學經濟跟AI的
To that Microsoft today
今天到那個Microsoft
To learn some advanced OpenAI
去學一些入的OpenAI
i mean now
我現在意思是說
I heard the refugee story
我聽到這難民故事
that
那個
Professor Wang gave me a lot
王教授給我很
Very
非常
deep impression
深刻的印象
But I want to ask a question is this
但是我要問一個問題是這樣
Because I am Tzu Chi
因為我是慈濟人
Some of us are brothers to help
我們有人是師兄去救助
and
而且
that
那個
about Ukraine
烏克蘭這事情
We are also going to pack
我們也是去打包
to donate
去捐助
then we are in
然後我們在
Syria also has
敘利亞也是有
that is
就是
We have a lot of seniors who have deep feelings over there.
我們有很多的師兄在那邊有很深的
this kind
這種
that
那個
to feel
感受
I mean
那我是說
Professor Wang, do you want to say
王教授有沒有想說
to experience
去體驗一下
go over there to see
到那邊去看
It's as if I followed my resignation hospital
這就好像我依我那個我們那個辭職醫院的
that one a while ago
前一陣子那個
The dean of nursing told me
護院長跟我講
say you
說你們
Like we resigned people is not to
像我們辭職人是不是到
Go to the hospital to feel the patients
到醫院去感受一下病人
Feel it, feel it, there is a question later
去感受一下那感受一下後面有一個問題來
I can extend my academic problems later because I study economics
後面可以延伸我學術上的問題因為我學經濟
This is
這是
Just like you are all academic
跟你們一樣就是都學術
But I've been slowly getting closer to that
可是一直慢慢會往往那個
There are only two parts to the food.
食物走就兩個部分啊就
Talking about life and doing it
活家講活理還有做
Remember all living beings and save all living beings
記眾眾生就救助眾生
Then I mean, the next question comes, that is,
那我意思說後面的一個問題來了就是說
Have you ever thought about the development of the aftermath?
你有沒有想過後戲的發展說怎麼其實這些
Refugees can become independent
難民 能夠獨立起來
because some refugees
因為有些難民
He is a high intellectual like those in Ukraine
他是像烏克蘭那些人有高知識分子
They are capable only because they are refugees
他們本身有能力只是說因為做難民
I don't want to be burdened by others
那也不願意被人一個負擔
so he is creative
所以他有創造力
So we want to follow up
所以我們想要後續的話
is to train him to be useful
就是訓練他能成有用的人
So some of the latter we are
所以後面的有些我們在
in tzu chi
在慈濟裡面
they are at school
他們就在那裡學校
then educate the child
然後教育的小孩
Then to derive from there is to say
然後從那裡面去衍生是說
Dead refugees don't do harm to another country
死難民不會對另外一個國家
Accepting a burden is a burden
接受的負擔是個負擔
but be creative
而是有創造力
and productive
而有生產力
but also to promote their economic development
而且還可以促進他們經濟發展
Professor Wang, do you want to say that you want to experience it?
王教授有沒有想說要去體驗一下
grateful
感恩
Thank you very much Mr. Li for this suggestion
非常謝謝李老師的這個建議
this i think
這個我想
OK, the vice president is here.
好 副院長在這邊
Research institutes can also host groups
研究院也可以主團
In fact, I think for researchers
其實我覺得對研究人員來說
it will be a very useful experience
這會是一個非常有用的經驗
and then it will be a very real experience
然後也會是一個非常真實的體驗
Then I myself am mainly in literature
那我自己一位主要在文學裡面
so i never had such a chance
所以我一直沒有這樣一個機會
but if any
但是如果有的話
I will also be willing to contact and try
我也會很願意的去接觸跟去嘗試
That's about what I'm going to say
那可是我要說的大概是這個
That is to say experience and contact
就是說體驗跟接觸
and long-term relationship
還有長期的相處
with refugees in our society
跟難民在我們的社會裡面
or ethnic minorities or immigrants
或者說少數民族或是外來移民
There will be some context here
這裡頭都會有一些脈絡上
or the difference in state
或狀態當中的差別
For example, if I go one day, two days, three days
譬如說我是去一天兩天三天
a week a month
一個禮拜一個月
There are some very substantial differences here
這裡頭會有一些很實質的差別
Let's say we have this
比方講我們有這個
friends who have been to refugee camps
曾經去過難民營的朋友
So when you go for a long time
這麼說當你去久了以後
You're numb to those stories
那些故事你就麻木了
You'll cry at first
一開始你會哭的嘻嘻嘩
then you feel
後來你就覺得
here we go again
又來了
ok
ok
then this is what i want
那這個是我想要
just say
就說
Well
呃
this is not to say
這不是說
it's not an excuse not to go
這不是作為不去的理由
i didn't mean that
我不是不是這個意思
that is
就是說
head this here
在這裡頭這個
The specific context may be very important to our experience
具體的脈絡可能對於我們的經驗是非常
an important factor
重要的一個因素
ok
ok
so uh
那麼呃
so of course i
所以我當然
support also uh
支持也呃
willing to assist these
願意協助這些
various access and
各種的訪問跟
uh auxiliary
呃輔助
but i think uh
但是我想呃
from a research point of view
從一個研究的角度來講
we'll have to think about it
我們會必須要去想一想
We are in this process when
我們在這個過程當
how did this process happen
這個這個過程是怎麼發生的
and in the process
以及在這個過程當中
what is our status
我們的狀態是什麼
this is an uprising
這個是起義
The rest is what you just mentioned
其餘的就是您剛剛提到
These are all kinds of auxiliary methods.
就是種種的這些輔助的這個方式
Well, of course I would agree
呃當然我也會是同意的
If they can be productive and so on
如果他們能夠有生產力等等的
all good of course
當然都很好
but this
但是這個
it's just us
不就恰恰是我們
uh mainstream discourse
呃主流論述
what you have been expecting and imagining
所不斷跟期待跟想像的嘛
then this is also
那這也是
uh i think we're talking about these few today
呃我覺得今天在談這些少數
or weak one-by-one problems
或是弱勢逐一的問題的時候
often difficult to overcome
往往很難克服的地方
The mainstream imagination is very clear and clear
主流的想像是非常的明確 清楚
and even have a high moral basis
而且甚至具有高度的道德基礎
think you see we've helped you so much
覺得你看我們已經幫助你這麼多
why don't you do it
你為什麼還不肯怎麼怎麼怎麼
Then from the context of literature
那麼從文學的脈絡裡面
What I'm trying to do is a
我嘗試的要做的是一種
A certain kind of experience that destroys others as much as possible
某一種盡可能的破盡他者的經驗
Can't say I'm totally capable of being the other
不能夠說我完全能夠成為他者
But a certain experience and attempt to destroy the other
但是某種破盡他者的經驗跟嘗試
may be what we want to provide to the society
可能是我們想要提供給這個社會
Some other thoughts outside of mainstream voices
在主流的聲音之外的一些其他的想法
I don't think this is necessarily a Hange situation.
那這個我覺得未必是一個漢革的狀況
It may just be an expansion or an addition
它可能只是一個擴張或是一個補充
But looking back, I feel that facing the refugee issue today
可是回過頭來我覺得今天面對難民問題
Often people say that in Europe they say
常常大家在講在歐洲他們說
This is called humanitarian crisis
這個叫做humanitarian crisis
humanitarian crisis
人道危機
But the problem is that there is a crisis, not humanity, right?
可是問題是有危機的不是人道對不對
These refugees aren't a crisis in themselves, are they?
這些難民本身也不是危機不是嗎
cause refugees
造成難民
The events of the crisis are actually the agents of the crisis
的那些事件 其實才是危機的使作用者
Right, so back to the definition of a refugee?
對吧 也就是說回到那個難民的定義
Refugees are those who cannot return home, or cannot return home
難民是回不了家 或不能回家的那些人
So if we create a condition today where they can go home
那如果我們今天創造一個他們能夠回家的條件
Is that the real solution to the refugee problem?
那是不是才是真正解決難民問題的一個方法
The question is, can we create such conditions?
那問題是我們能不能創造這樣的條件呢
Then I think this is not just a face
那這個我覺得就不僅僅是一個面對
A state in which you want to solve a problem that has come before you
一個已經來到面前的問題你要解決的那樣的一個狀態
but go one step further and go back
而是更進一步的去返回去
What is the premise of reflecting on the whole construction problem
反思整個構造問題的那個前提是什麼
That's what I think we hope to provide to the society
那這也是我覺得我們希望能夠提供給這個社會的
not just go
不是僅僅的去
How to say, use the method of posting OK to solve a problem that has already
怎麼講 以貼OK蹦的方式去解決一個已經
Imminent problem Instead, put this imminent problem
迫在眉睫的問題 而是說把這個迫在眉睫的問題
While solving the problem, we also think a little bit more deeply.
在解決的同時 同時也想得更深遠一點點
See if it can be accessed from the root, or from a relatively large structure
看能不能從根上面 或是說從一個比較大的結構當中
to reimagine and understand the problem
來重新想像跟理解這個問題
Maybe we'll get some different answers
也許我們會得到一些不同的答案
this female friend
這位女性朋友
Maintain one man, one woman, one woman, one man
維持一男一女一女一男
so
這樣
Hello Professor Wang
王教授你好
I'm Shi Jiacheng
我是石家成
I am a
我是一個
It's like a background engineer doing international aid
像是背景師在做國際援助的
just the staff
就是工作人員
i feel like i just
我覺得我剛剛的
I feel very grateful for today's speech
覺得很謝謝今天的演講
Then
然後
I think I may have missed some information just now
我覺得我剛剛可能有漏掉一些訊息
that is
就是說
Professor Wang just mentioned
王教授剛剛有提到
in literature
就是在文學裡面
that is
就是
of these stories
的這些故事
That's what I just heard a keyword
那就是剛剛我聽到一個關鍵字
is to tell these stories
是說這些故事
Maybe he was consumed
可能他有被消費
or being
或是說被
is that there may be a need for a standard
就是可能需要有一個標準的
It's the story of a refugee
就是一個難民的這樣的故事
or
或是
just mentioned some
剛剛有提到一些
some different sketches
不同的一些勾勒
such a picture of
的這樣的畫面
But I still don't quite understand
但我還是不是很明白說
These
這些
literary
文學的
experience with this refugee
經驗跟這個難民
Except for the eligibility of this refugee
就除了說這個難民的資格
how to be identified
如何被認定之外
for their freedom and dignity
就是對於他們獲得的自由和尊嚴而言
do you think this has any relationship
您覺得這是有什麼樣的關係嗎
yes this is the first question
對這是第一個問題
Then the second question is to say
然後第二個問題是說
because from the food
因為從食物的
If we look at it from the point of view of food
我們就是食物的觀點來看的話
that is
就是
current refugee problem
現在碰到的難民問題
A more modern refugee problem
比較現代的難民問題
maybe like climate refugees
可能是像氣候難民
caused these crises in the mediterranean
造成地中海的這些危機
Then
然後
not a crisis
又不是危機
that is
就是
It's Shah
就是沙哈
Northern Sahara
北沙哈拉的
Anyway it is
反正就是
Some of Africa's climate refugees
非洲的一些氣候難民
is to Europe
就是往歐洲
then the crisis in syria
然後敘利亞的危機
and then
然後就是
like yemen
比如說葉門
or some longer-term issues
或是一些比較長久的問題
Or maybe even like the earthquake in Türkiye
或是說甚至像土耳其的地震
Then something like this happens
然後發生這樣子的狀況
you just mentioned
您剛剛有提到說
In fact, most of them are low-to-medium
就是其實大部分是一些中低
Developing countries host the most refugees
開發國家收容的難民最多
I can understand that
那我可以理解就是說
literature just can take a while
文學就是可能需要一段時間
just might be
就是可能才會被
These are the ones integrated into the society
就是融入社會的這些
created by descendants of refugees
難民的後裔所創造出來
But what I want to understand is to say
可是對我想理解是說
Are you doing this research for
您在做這些研究對於
some of the current refugees
當下的難民的一些
Event is what kind of thought?
事件就是有什麼樣的想法嗎
Thanks
謝謝
very happy
非常高興
There are many friends from the food industry here today
今天在場有很多食物界的朋友
so i was a little surprised
所以我有一點意外
but also very happy
但是也非常的高興
Because obviously we're in this society
因為顯然我們在這個社會裡頭
There's a lot actually on this subject
有很多其實在這個問題上面
have many devoted friends
有很多投入的朋友
Then I think two questions
那我覺得兩個問題
Simply put
簡單這麼說
The previous question was about the story itself
前面的那個問題是關於故事的本身
how about these stories
就是這些故事怎麼樣
some of these stories
就是這些故事的一些
what should i say
應該怎麼說呢
its typicality or its exemplary
它的典型性或它的典範性
become a
成為一種
The kind of consumption I just mentioned in the speech
我剛剛在演講裡頭說的這種消費的
consumption of spectacle
奇觀性的這種消費
That part is for
那這個一部分是針對於
As for how the refugees themselves are subject to the image of these refugees
對於難民本身怎麼樣受制於這些難民形象的這個
critique and analysis
批判跟分析而來的
That is to say, many refugees may feel that they are being forced into a
就是說很多難民可能會覺得說他們被強迫放在一個
or should i say
或應該這麼說吧
be compelled or said to be expected to perform a
被強迫或說被期待去表演一個
good refugee such an image
好的難民這樣的一個形象
This also contains some brave qualities
這也包含一些勇敢的特質
contains some gentle qualities
包含一些溫柔的特質
Contains some of these traits of tolerance to trauma
包含一些耐受創傷的這些特質
But not every refugee can fully present such a trait
可是並不是每一個難民都能夠充分的呈現這樣的一個特質
But we will in these existing stories
可是我們會在這些已有的故事當中
To understand or recognize and construct a basic concept for refugees
去認識或認知跟建構一個我們對於難民的一個基本的
thoughts and status
想法跟狀態
So this imaginary or constructed image
所以這個想像或建構出來的這樣的一個形象
with the actual
跟實際的這個
Is there a kind of experience
經驗中間有沒有一種
Consideration
一方面是對價關係
You have to meet this thing before I can accept you
你要符合這個東西我才能夠接受你
Or will he form an oppressive relationship?
或者說他會不會形成一種壓迫關係
Because it's like this, I can't match it
因為是這個樣子我沒有辦法符合所以
how i have to
我必須如何如何如何
Then this is what I want in this research
那這個是我想在這個研究裡面
trying to
試圖要
just one of the opening
張開的其中的一點而已
OK
OK
That is to say, we are often
就是說我們往往在
Often in the narrative, it actually regulates our
往往在敘事當中其實也規範了我們
Acceptable and understandable range
能夠接受跟理解的範圍
OK
OK
The other one actually returns
那另外一個其實回到
the food problem
食物的這個問題
Of course I have no actual food experience so it's hard to get in
當然我沒有實際的食物經驗所以很難在
food above
食物上面
make a nice response
做一個很好的回應
But what I can probably say is that
但是我大概可以說的是說
to Ukraine
以烏克蘭
Take Ukraine as an example
以烏克蘭為例子這麼講
western fast
西方很快的
Receiving Ukrainian refugees with open arms
張開雙手接受烏克蘭難民
But from 2013 to 15 years
可是從2013年15年
The Syrian Refugee Crisis
這個敘利亞難民危機
Up to now, virtual nanometer has still become a
到現在 虛擬奈米依然成為一個
Issues not adequately addressed within Europe
在歐洲境內未能夠充分解決的問題
How to explain the difference here
這裡的差異該怎麼解釋
Or how to make the difference here
或說這裡的差異該怎麼樣邁落化的
Let's see what exactly causes these differences
讓我們看見究竟是什麼造成的這些差異
Then this is probably facing reality
那這個大概是面對現實狀態
one may not be a good answer
一個可能不是一個很好的回答
But that is to say, if we face the reality with courage
可是就是說如果勉勵地去應對現實的話
I think the critical thinking provided in the research
我覺得在研究裡面所提供的這些批判性的思考
In fact, it may not be impossible to put it in a real field to test
其實未必不能夠放到現實的場域以頭去檢驗
Maybe we might be talking too much about these thoughts
也許我們可能這些想法說得太過了
Then reality can slap us in the face and tell us that's not the case
那麼現實可以把我們一巴掌告訴我們說不是如此的
Then we'd love to take a reality check, too.
那我們也很樂意接受現實的檢驗
But it is also possible that such a presupposition or imagination
但也有可能這樣的一個預設或想像
It is possible that in this real experience
有可能在現實的這個經驗當中
help us see something different
幫助我們看見一些不同的東西
Of course we are also very happy
我們當然也非常的高興
In this sense, I think it is actually necessary
那在這意義上我覺得其實是需要
The academia and the food industry have more cooperation and expectations
學界跟食物界有更多的合作跟期待
In the past, we worked on the issue of migrant workers
以往我們在做移工的問題上面
In fact, there are many cooperations in the food industry
其實有很多的食物界的這個合作
But in Naiming because of his international nature
可是在奈明因為他的這個國際性質的這個
Relationships are also less accessible
關係也比較不容易接觸得到
This may require more efforts from us
這個可能還需要我們有更多的努力
thank you very much for your question
那非常謝謝您的提問
You are the gentleman in front of this society
這個 社會你是前面這位先生
our last three questions
我們就最後三個問題
The first one
第一位
hello i'm a biology student
你好 我是學生物的
So I guess the first thing we think
所以我想第一件事情是我們認為
We are all struggling for survival
我們都是 struggle for survive
all creatures are the same
所有的生物都是一樣的
And the second thing that always comes to my mind is
然後第二個常在我心裡想的是
franklin once said
弗蘭克林講過一句話
That is, if you are unwilling to pay any obligation for freedom
就是如果不願意為自由付出任何義務
this man does not deserve to be free
這個人不值得自由
then my question
那我的問題
Once when I was arguing with someone
有一次我在跟人家吵架的時候
I say that maybe it's offensive to some people
我說這樣也許對某些人是冒犯
But I think Ms. Nongyuntai also said
但是我想農運台女士也講過
Dajiang Dahai is a refugee
大江大海他是難民
I said it was just refugees with guns
我就說當時來的不過是戴槍的難民
He told me that if you wear a gun, you are not a refugee.
他就跟我說戴槍就不是難民了
I want to ask the teacher
我想請問老師
if i give up defending myself today
如果我今天放棄保衛我自己
to be a refugee
才能成為難民
or am i a refugee today
還是我今天是個難民
But I'm willing to pick up a gun and defend myself
但是我願意拿槍起來保衛我自己
I can get out of refugee status
我就可以脫離難民這個身份
good question
很好 問題
Looks like the gift from today's seminar is pretty good
看起來今天研究會提供的禮物非常好
So everyone's questions are very enthusiastic.
所以大家的提問非常的踴躍
let me put it this way
讓我這麼說吧
If we go back to the previous UN-related definitions
如果我們回到前面聯合國相關的定義
Refugees have nothing to do with having a gun or not
難民跟拿不拿槍是沒有什麼關係的
But that doesn't mean it doesn't matter that the refugees who are asking for trouble won't matter.
但不表示說討難的難民不會有什麼關係
or a knife
或是小刀
Right
對吧
creatures need to survive
生物需要生存
The creature will find his way out
生物會尋找一條他的出路
This is what I think everyone can agree with and accept.
這個是我想大家可以同意跟接受的
But to what extent do creatures
但是生物要做到什麼樣的程度
to save his life
來保全他的生命
or expand his livelihood
或擴張他的生路
I think there is an ethical issue here
這裡我覺得有一個倫理問題
OK that
OK 那
We generally think of refugees as victims, right?
我們一般會覺得難民都是受難者對不對
Right
對吧
But Erlan told us
但是二蘭告訴我們說
How to escape the image of the victim
如何脫離受難者的形象
Make yourself famous first
首先要讓自己變得有名
how to become famous
要怎麼樣變得有名
you are going to steal
你要去偷竊也好
It's good to go to the robber
要去強盜也好
it doesn't matter
都沒有關係
as long as i can
只要我能夠
was seen
被看見了
my voice can be heard
我的聲音能夠被聽到了
I can how
我就能夠如何如何
will be able to
就能夠
have this condition to discuss my rights
擁有一個討論我權利的這個條件
that's where i want to go
那這裡就是我想要去
Consider that
考慮的就是說
Is there an ethic in being a refugee?
做一個難民有沒有一種倫理
That sounds weird too, doesn't it?
這聽起來也很奇怪對不對
you already
你都已經
You are already a refugee, what ethics are you talking about?
已經是難民了 你還談什麼倫理呢
but this is not
可是這個不
Do you mean being a refugee?
難道說做了難民就
no more ethics?
不用倫理了嗎
It's weird not to say the other way around, isn't it?
反過來講不也很奇怪是不是
So
那麼
So I think your question
所以我想你的這個提問
Of course, there is a very realistic context and context in Taiwan.
當然有一個很台灣現實的脈絡跟語境
this part i
這個部分我
I
我
Let me put it this way, let me not touch him so directly
這麼說吧 容我不那麼直接的去碰觸他
But I come and go in the opposite direction
但是我反一個方向來去
The way to discuss this would probably be to say
討論這個問題的方式大概會是說
Um
嗯
when we have
當我們已經
Enter
進入到
When in a situation where you might become a refugee
可能成為難民的這樣一個處境的時候
Well
呃
Whether to hold a gun or not may already be another question.
拿不拿槍可能已經是另外的一個問題了
Come
來
what we hope is
我們希望的是
such an experience
這樣的一個經驗
Don't happen to us though it sounds selfish
不要發生在我們身上 雖然這聽起來有點自私
as if someone else
好像別人
It doesn't matter if you're a refugee, but we don't want
是難民沒有關係 但我們不要
but instead of saying
可是不是這樣 而是說
When we can not go through this situation
當我們可以不要經歷這樣的處境的時候
or when we hope not to go through such a journey
或我們希望不要經歷這樣的一個歷程的時候
what should we do now
那我們現在該做什麼
then i think
那我覺得
So this has nothing to do with holding a gun
所以這個跟拿不拿槍是
not completely irrelevant
不是完全不相關
But not so directly a cozorelation
但是不是那麼直接的一個cozorelation
With a gun, of course, you can kill a bloody road, right?
拿槍固然可以也許殺出一條血路吧
barely say so
勉強這麼說
But what kind of road will the bloody road be?
但殺出來的血路會是什麼樣的路
Is it the way to live
是不是適合生活的路
This is also what I think many of the refugee stories provide us with a
這也是我覺得很多的難民故事提供給我們一個
Very different or bloody inspirations and experiences
很不一樣的或是說很血淋淋的一些啟發跟經驗
So I think I'll answer this question for now
所以我想這個問題我暫且這樣回答
hope you are satisfied
希望你能夠滿意
If you are not satisfied, we can discuss it in private.
那如果不滿意我們也私下可以再討論
ok thanks
好嗎 謝謝
The last two questions this classmate
最後兩個問題這位同學
The classmate in white clothes
白色衣服這位同學
Hello, teacher. I am the candidate for the blood test.
老師你好我是那個血測從考生
then want to ask
然後想請教
There have been extreme terrorist attacks in Europe in recent years
歐洲這幾年有發生過極其的恐攻
It's all about refugees
都是跟難民有關
Let me tell you the truth, if it happened in Taiwan
那我說實話如果是發生在台灣的話
Personally, I'd be terrified of refugees
以我個人角度我會對難民產生恐懼
So what kind of mentality should we have in order to trust the refugee group?
那我們該以怎麼樣的心態才有辦法去信任難民這個群體
And let's get this stereotype out of our minds
然後讓我們打從心裡消除這種刻板印象
because the fact is that it happened
因為事實就是有發生過
Mr. Xie
謝老師
This problem is mainly a hero out of a teenager
這個問題主要是英雄出少年
So the tough question comes from the youngest questioner
所以艱難的問題來自於最年輕的這個提問者
this stuff is really hard
這個東西確實很難
I think this is of course also challenging our bottom line as human beings, right?
我覺得這個當然也在挑戰我們作為人的底線在哪裡對不對
That is, assuming your freshman experience was such an encounter
就是說假設你的新生的經驗是這樣的一個遭遇
And it is a clear relationship
而且是一個明確的這個關係的話
For example, tell me something about me
比方講我的什麼什麼
It's because of this that he was sacrificed or injured.
就是因為這樣子而犧牲或是受傷了
Of course, that is a very clear signal to you, right?
那當然對你來講那個是一個在明確不過的一個訊號對不對
then you'd like to say that you can keep those dangers or fears out of the equation
那你會希望說能夠把這些危險或恐懼排除在外
that but i think on the one hand
那但是我想一方面是
Is that so?
是這麼說吧
If the history you just told is true
如果你剛剛講的那個歷史是真的
I can't remember now
我現在一直想不起來
is it true
是不是真的如此
but suppose you
但假設你
just say
就這麼說
i believe what you say is true
我相信你講的是真的
Then I can probably just say
那麼我大概只能夠說
Not every refugee is a terrorist
不是每一個難民都是恐怖主義者
Another one is to say
另外一個就是說
What is the context of these things?
那發生這些事情的脈絡是什麼
How do we understand that these things happened
我們怎麼樣理解這些事情的發生
not just focus or focus on
不僅僅是關注或聚焦在
those who caused these events
那些造成這些事件的
identity of the author
者的身份上面
because these identities are probably the easiest to identify
因為這些身份可能是最容易辨識
easiest to see
最容易看見
easiest to pick out
最容易被挑出來
as different from us
作為跟我們不相同的
that part
那一個部分
to be noticed
來被注意到的
But perhaps more importantly
可是可能更重要的是
what caused
什麼東西造成了
This specific identity and group
這個特定的身份跟群體
to carry out such a
來進行了這樣的一個
The tragedy we don't want to see
我們不願意看到的悲劇
then this may be
那這個或許是
I feel that in all encounters
我覺得在所有遭遇到
when tragic events
悲劇性事件的時候
We should all actually think about it
我們都應該其實想一想的
But at 911
不過在911
In fact, there was a big
其實當時有一個很大的
Reflection Except within the United States
反思 除了在美國境內
Everyone is very anti-terrorism outside
大家非常的反恐怖主義之外
More often people think of
更多的時候大家想的是
Why did these people suddenly come to America
為什麼這些人突然來到了美國
What the United States is doing in the Middle East
美國在中東做了什麼事情
make these so-called terrorists
使得這些所謂的恐怖分子
All were able to enter the United States through the US security check.
都能夠通過美國安檢進入到了美國
even acquired these resources and capabilities for military operations
甚至獲得了軍事行動的這些資源跟能力
I think it's something else
那這個我覺得其他事
The direction we should ask and pursue
我們應該發問跟追問的這個方向
thanks then our last question
謝謝 那我們最後一個問題
Mr. Society, wear a mask, Mr. Society
社會先生 戴口罩 社會先生
Hello teacher, thank you very much for your speech today
老師你好 很謝謝老師今天的演講
Brilliant and then I have a question
非常精采 然後我有一個問題
It just happened to be in my heart for a while
剛好就其實放在我心中一陣子
Then just because of the princess, a friend of mine went
然後剛好是因為公主 我一個朋友去
He is a reporter from Taiwan
他是台灣的記者
Then he himself became very interested in refugee issues
然後他自己對難民問題很有興趣
So he spent a lot of time in these years
所以他這幾年花了很多時間
Find ways to interview and research countries around the world
自己去想辦法採訪跟研究世界各國
That includes Syria, Ukraine
那包含敘利亞、烏克蘭
Then there is the African country Afghanistan and so on
然後還有非洲國家阿富汗等等
Then there are South American
然後也有南美的
Then
然後
And because I'm friends with him
然後因為我跟他是朋友
so i have seen him write something
所以我有看過他寫了一些東西
Of course there are some things that we can understand
那當然有些東西是比較我們可以理解的
Then there are many things that just echo the teacher's question
然後也有很多東西剛好呼應老師的問題
In fact, the issue he wanted to discuss happened to be a lecture with the teacher today.
他其實想要探討的問題剛好跟老師今天演講
The theme is like
主題很像就是
Refugees aren't just one or two stereotypes actually
難民是不是只能有一個或兩個的刻板印象其實
It's not that he actually has various faces
其實不是他其實有各種面貌
These appearances are all in the mainstream media or
那這些面貌都在主流的媒體或者是
interests outside political ideology
政治意識形態的興趣之外
Then his writing is the multi-headed appearance he wants to present.
那他這個書寫就是想要呈現的多頭面貌
But I am particularly fond of the two characters in his record
但是我特別對他的紀錄裡面的兩個人物的
speech to
對講話
special interest is
特別感興趣就是
What surprises me about these two is that they say they are refugees but they are true to themselves
這兩個人讓我surprise的是說他們是難民但是他們對自己的
Dare to fight for rights or what he deserves
權利或者他應該得到的東西很敢去爭取
That one is like you just mentioned
那一個是像您剛剛有提到就是說
One of them is a Syrian refugee
其中一個是敘利亞難民
He saw the Ukrainian name in Europe
他看到了烏克蘭的那名在歐洲
When you are taken care of relatively warmly
得到很相對來說很熱情的照顧的時候
when accepting
跟接納的時候
he is very angry
他很憤怒
He said why the same European country
他就說為什麼同樣是那名歐洲國家
Much better for Ukraine than us
對烏克蘭比我們好很多
He was very angry for asking
他就這樣問很憤怒
of course no answer
當然沒有答案
But it's surprising to me that it says
但是對我來說很驚訝的是說
Of course it's also the other way around
當然這也反過來
Forcing myself to challenge my own cognition
逼迫我自己去挑戰我自己的認知
I just wanted to say what's so weird about it
我就想說這有什麼好奇怪
they are european countries
他們是歐洲國家
There is also a Christian civilization
同樣有基督教文明
same white complexion
同樣是白色膚色
then to
然後對
But he doesn't think that's a reason
但是他並不覺得那是個理由
He angrily questioned
他非常憤怒地去質問這樣
And then another example is a guy from Neglia
然後另外一個例子是一個耐吉利亞的人
He is actually strictly speaking
他其實嚴格來說
not your typical refugee
不是典型的難民
He is going to study in England
他是去英國念書
But since then it happened to him that he had a disease
但是因為後來他發生他有種疾病
that disease if he goes back to negilia
那種疾病如果他回到耐吉利亞
There is no way to get proper care
是沒有辦法得到妥善的照顧的
because his brother died
因為他的親兄弟就因此過世
So there seems to be a law in the UK that says
所以英國好像有個法律是說
You can stay in the UK for medical reasons
你可以用醫療的理由留在英國
but
但是
However, due to various technical problems
但是因為各種技術上問題
He was not accepted by the British government
他沒有被英國政府接受
So he went to court with the British government for many years
所以他就跟英國政府打官司打了很多年
Then in this interview he said
然後這個採訪裡面他就講
He complained that he thought the British government had not properly
他就抱怨他認為英國政府沒有妥善的
give him his due rights
賦予他應有的權利
So he angrily criticized the British government
所以他就很憤怒的批評英國政府
And he also has the support of a lot of Britons
然後他也得到很多英國人的支持
I feel that the British government is not doing a good job.
就覺得說英國政府做得不好
should give him the right
應該給他權利沒有
Caused him to pretend to be a youth to go to court
導致他圖號了青春去打官司
Normal life and due development are thus on the wheel
正常的生活跟應有的發展都因此輪上
Then I got curious and said
然後我就很好奇就是說
Why is this guy not actually a British citizen?
為什麼這些人其實他並不是英國公民
Not a citizen of Ukraine or any other country
也不是烏克蘭或哪一國公民
But he thinks he can have
但是他認為他自己可以有
great right to demand even he can criticize
很大的權利去要求甚至他可以去批評
Then also got a case like the British
然後也得到了像英國人的case
He is also supported by British citizens
他也得到英國公民的支持
Seems like the Guardian also reported his case.
好像衛報也有報到他的案例
I'm just curious, why?
我就好奇是說一來是說為什麼
These refugees feel that they have
這些難民覺得自己有
That power and right
那個power跟right
Then another reason is
然後另外一個原因是
Another question is that
另外一個問題就是說
Is it true that European countries have developed a
是不是歐洲國家這幾年已經發展出一種
A new discourse looks at the matter of citizenship
新的論述去看待公民權這件事情
so that as you just discussed is to say
以至於就像您剛剛討論的就是說
like A'olan would criticize
像阿俄蘭就會批評說
If you don't have citizenship you don't have human rights
如果你沒有公民權你就沒有人權這東西
that sovereignty
那主權
Should human rights and sovereignty be tied together?
人權跟主權這東西應該綁在一起嗎
Or in fact, European countries can do better
還是其實歐洲國家可以做得更好
Then you mentioned a little bit
那您剛才稍微有提到的一些
The latest discussion of that in Europe
那個歐洲最新的討論
But can the teacher be there more?
但是就老師可不可以在那邊再多
Let’s talk a little more about the past few years in Europe
多講掉一點就是歐洲這幾年
Discussion on the relationship between human rights and refugees
在對人權跟難民的關係上的論述
Is there some new development like this?
是不是有些新的發展這樣子
Thanks
謝謝
OK, I will simply add something like this
好我簡單的做一點這樣的補充
the first is
第一個是
The refugee problem is in Europe as in America as in Asia
難民問題在歐洲跟在美洲跟在亞洲
is a very different configuration
是很不一樣的configuration
OK
OK
Well, in Europe I think there is a special place
那麼在歐洲我覺得有一個特別的地方
because it is the eu
因為它是歐盟
So when refugees come in
所以當難民進入以後
It really only needs to be accepted
它其實只要被接受
it may be conditioned to be able to move
它有可能有條件能夠移動
Or he may also choose to speak to him
或者是說他也可能去選擇對他來講
Conditions will be better to move
條件會比較好的地方去移動
OK, then this is what I want in the real thing
OK 那這個是我想在現實物裡面
Some examples we can see
我們可以看到的一些例子
that means he's here
就是說他來到了
For example, he crossed the Mediterranean from Syria
譬如說他從敘利亞度過了地中海
came to greece
來到了希臘
In fact, it is because Greece is relatively easy to get to.
其實是因為希臘這個地方比較容易抵達
in many senses
在很多意義上面
And it's a route that's been traveled many times
而且是一個已經被走過很多次的路線
So here we can actually see
所以在這裡頭其實我們也可以看到
Refugees have some knowledge accumulation
難民有一些知識積累
Is he has long the path of this refugee
就是他有長時間的這個難民的路徑
Formed a whole set of this process
形成了一整套的這個流程
if we may say so
如果我們可以這麼說的話
Then this process includes our selection
那這個流程裡頭就包含了我們選擇
It's where the refugees choose to settle.
就是難民選擇去哪裡落腳
where to move
到哪裡移動
and where to get the identity
然後在哪裡取得身份
some different options like this
這樣的一些不同的選擇
including this one we were just talking about about North Korea
包含我們剛剛在談北韓的這個
When this experience of North Korean defectors
脫北者的這個經驗的時候
In fact, many North Korean defectors, of course
其實很多的脫北者當然一開始
I want to go to South Korea
都希望能夠去南韓
Then he opened his hands at the beginning
然後他一開始也是張開雙手
hug these defectors
擁抱這些脫北者
Because this can prove that South Korea is
因為這個可以證明南韓是
It is the most reasonable and legal representative of the two Korean governments, right?
就是兩韓政府當中最合理跟合法的代表對不對
This is very exhausting for the relationship between the two Koreas.
這跟兩韓關係是很累盡的
But because too many people came
可是因為來的人太多了
So the governments of the two Koreas feel that this will create another kind of fear and crisis
所以兩韓政府覺得這會形成另外一種的恐懼跟危機
So he started shutting down the flow of North Korean defectors into South Korea.
於是他開始關閉了脫北者進入南韓的管道
This made it impossible for these North Korean defectors to leave smoothly.
使得這些脫北者沒有辦法順利的離開了
From Taiwan to North Korea to China and then to South Korea
離台朝鮮來到中國然後去到南韓
So he started moving elsewhere
於是他就開始往別的地方去移動
So what I'm going to say is to go back to your question
那麼所以我要說的就是說回到你剛剛的那個問題
A very core place in it is
裡頭一個很核心的地方是
Refugees are not people without knowledge
難民不是沒有知識的人
This is the first one I think we should be very aware of
這個是我想第一個我們應該很清楚認識到的
That is, refugees are not only people without knowledge
就是難民不僅是不是沒有知識的人
And they probably have a whole lot of knowledge about fleeing
而且他們可能有一些有一整套的關於逃難的知識
we don't have
是我們沒有的
So when I read topics related to refugee studies
所以我讀難民研究相關的題目的時候
I was surprised that when many refugees fled
我很驚訝的是原來很多難民逃難的時候
is wearing a mobile phone
是戴著手機的
Then there are cell phones so you have GPS
然後有手機所以你有 GPS
then where can how how how how how how
然後在哪裡可以怎麼樣怎麼樣怎麼樣
then this is
那這個是
The thing we didn't think about when we wanted refugees before
以前我們在想要難民的時候不會想到的這個事情
So I think the part about keeping pace with the times
那所以我覺得與時俱進的部分來講
Actually in Europe
其實在歐洲
The first one, of course, is that the understanding of refugees keeps pace with the times.
第一個當然就是對難民的認識的一個與時俱進
In addition, in Europe because of such a state
另外也就是在歐洲因為這樣的一個狀態
So Europe is constantly
所以歐洲不斷的
The more progressive person
比較進步的這個人士
What is actually being discussed is
其實在討論的是說
How do we carry out a so-called all-European management
我們怎麼樣進行一個所謂的全歐洲的management
Don't let all the refugees go through it, let's say italy
不要讓所有的難民通通其中在比方講意大利
or among them in greece
或是其中在希臘
can share
能不能分攤
Shared among EU countries
歐盟各國境內彼此來分攤
Form a mechanism to enable these people to have a suitable placement
形成一個機制使得這些人能夠有一個合適的安置
I understand that this is still under discussion
那這個還在討論當中就我理解
Such a proposition actually encountered a lot of backlash.
那這樣的一個主張其實也碰到了很多的反彈
Maybe Germany is comparatively speaking
可能德國是相較來講比較
Welcome is a country that is more willing to tolerate and accept
Welcome比較願意寬容接納的這個國家
But some other countries may not be so willing, like Italy
可是其他的部分國家可能就不那麼願意比方好像意大利
so here maybe
所以在這裡可能
Probably have to go back to the whole EU
大概就得要回到整個歐盟境內
Some special situations in each country
各個國家的一些特殊的狀況
come to understand these
來去理解這些
Individual country situation relative to refugee movements
個別國家的狀況跟難民移動的相對關係
I think this is probably what I can provide
這個我想大概是我能夠提供的一些
Simply add like this
簡單的補充這樣
thanks for your question
謝謝你的問題
well thank you very much for this tonight
好 今天晚上非常謝謝這個
Professor Wang gave us a wonderful speech
王教授給我們一個精彩的演講
offers us much to reflect on
提供我們很多的反思
So let's applaud him now
所以我們現在就鼓掌來謝謝他
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you very much for your participation
非常感謝各位的參與